<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The second part of the interest of England, in the matter of religion, unfolded in a deliberative discourse, proving that it is not agreeable to sound reason to prefer the contracted and dividing interest of one party, before the general  interest of Protestantism, and of the whole kingdom of England, in which the Episcopal and Presbyterian parties may be happily united. /</title>
            <title>Interest of England in the matter of religion. Part 2</title>
            <author>Corbet, John, 1620-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 131 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 67 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80550</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6264</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1857_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210384</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99869189</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99869189</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170477</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80550)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170477)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 231:E1857[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The second part of the interest of England, in the matter of religion, unfolded in a deliberative discourse, proving that it is not agreeable to sound reason to prefer the contracted and dividing interest of one party, before the general  interest of Protestantism, and of the whole kingdom of England, in which the Episcopal and Presbyterian parties may be happily united. /</title>
                  <title>Interest of England in the matter of religion. Part 2</title>
                  <author>Corbet, John, 1620-1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>132, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G.T. and are to be sold at the Rose and Crown in St Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>J.C. = John Corbet.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March. 10".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian union --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Protestants --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Presbyterianism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170477:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Second Part OF THE <hi>Intereſt</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> In the Matter of Religion, Unfolded in a Deliberative Diſcourſe, <hi>PROVING, That it is not agreeable to ſound Reaſon to prefer the Contracted and Dividing In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of one Party, before the general Intereſt of</hi> Proteſtantiſm, <hi>and of the whole Kingdom of England, in which the</hi> Epiſcopal <hi>and</hi> Presbyterian <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties may be happily United.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written by <hi>J. C.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>G. T.</hi> and are to be ſold at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in St <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170477:2"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:170477:2"/>
            <p>I Intreat the Reader to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, That in theſe Diſcourſes I do not mention Parties to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Diviſion, but to procure <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; That neceſſity compels me to uſe thoſe names of difference, which I heartily wiſh might be no more remembred: But whilſt diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing Parties laſt, names of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference cannot ceaſe, and to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear their uſe is to little purpoſe. My buſineſs is to take things as I find them, and to ſtate the Caſe between the Diſſenters, and to ſhew how far they agree, and how little they differ, for this end, That Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties (both Name and Thing) might ceaſe for ever.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:170477:3"/>
            <p>Moreover, as I uſe not the name of <hi>Presbyterian</hi> in way of glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſo I uſe not the name of <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> or <hi>Prelatiſt</hi> in way of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, but meerly for diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſake; and I have warrant for it from the friends of <hi>Prelacy,</hi> with whom it is not unuſual to mention the name of <hi>Prelate</hi> in an honourable Sence.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:170477:3"/>
            <head>The Second Part of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of <hi>England</hi> in the Matter of Religion.</head>
            <p>THe former Treatiſe of <hi>the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of</hi> England <hi>in the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Religion,</hi> makes known the way of peace, in the reconciling of thoſe two grand Parties, the <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopal</hi> and <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> which, if made one, would take in, and carry along the ſtrength of almoſt the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The whole ſtructure thereof reſts upon theſe Poſitions as its ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quate Foundation.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>That whilſt the two forenamed Parties remain divided, both the Proteſtant Religion, and the Kingdom of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>is divided againſt it ſelf.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:170477:4"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>That the</hi> Presbyterians <hi>cannot be rooted out, nor their Intereſt ſwallowed up, whileſt the State of</hi> England <hi>remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Proteſtant.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>That their ſubverſion, if it be poſsible to be accompliſhed, will be very pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the Proteſtant Religion, and the Kingdom of</hi> England.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>That the Coalition of both Parties into one may be effected by an equal accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation, without repugnancy to their conſcientious Principles on either ſide, in ſo much that nothing juſtifiable by Religion or ſound Reaſon can put a bar to this deſirable Union.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Now for as much as political mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are involved in difficulties and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexities, by variety of complicated concernments, all which ſhould be thorowly ſeen, and diligently examin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and compared; and becauſe the minds of men are commonly pre-inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170477:4"/>or at leaſt much byaſſed in theſe matters, and thereupon are not eaſily removed from their pre-conceived o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, I could not reſt ſatisfied, as having done my part in this healing Work, unleſs beſides a firm and clear proof of things in general, I endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour a deeper impreſſion, and more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual perſwaſion, by ſearching on e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſide, by preſſing up cloſe to thoſe cloſeſt concernments and moſt obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate prejudices that oppoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and by opening the paſſages, and making the way plain to this deſired Pacification.</p>
            <p>It is a grave and weighty ſaying of the Duke of <hi>Rhoan,—Princes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the people; and Intereſt commands the Princes. The knowledge of this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt is as much more raiſed above that of Princes Actions, as they themſelves are above the people. A Prince may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive himſelf, the Councel may be corrupt, but the Interest alone never faileth: ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as it is well or ill underſtood, it maketh States to live or dye.</hi>—Accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170477:5"/>to this ſaying it is matter of life and death political to the Kingdom of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> as it doth well or ill underſtand its own Intereſt: In this deliberation two Intereſts exceeding great and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, offer themſelves unto us. They are diſtinct, yet not divided; but they embrace each other, and they both ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently belong to us, and are undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly to be owned by us. The one is Religious, the other Civil. The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer is that of the Proteſtant Religion, and the latter is that of this Kingdom. Wherefore in this Inquiry, the main and fundamental point of knowledge lies in diſcerning the true ſtate of both. Now the true ſtate of any Society lies in the Univerſality, or the whole Body, not in any contracting or ſub-dividing part thereof: And the Intereſt lies in the conſervation and advancement of the Univerſality.</p>
            <p>Hereupon this Queſtion ariſeth, which is the great Caſe and Queſtion of the preſent times,</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:170477:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Whether we ſhould aſſert the contracted and dividing Intereſt of one Party, before the general interest of Protestantiſm, and of the whole Kingdom of</hi> England, <hi>in which the</hi> Epiſcopal <hi>and</hi> Presbyterian <hi>Parties may be happily United.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Be it here obſerved, That ſuch is the joynt ſtock of both Parties in things of greateſt moment, that by declining extreams on both hands, the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion may be ſtrengthened, with Unity in Doctrine, Worſhip and Diſcipline, among all its profeſſors, and the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> by an inviolable Union between theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive Parties may flouriſh in peace and plenty: for thoſe diſcords that divide the members and diſtract the whole body, will ceaſe; and thoſe common concernments which tend to uphold and encreaſe the Univerſality, will be acknowledged and purſued.</p>
            <p>To turn aſide from this common Intereſt of the whole body, to thoſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170477:6"/>inferiour partial ones, is to ſet up the trade of Monopolizers, which inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably brings this miſchief, that a few grow rich by impoveriſhing the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth; and this inconvenience alſo to them that follow the trade, that they grow rich upon the ſudden, but are not ſecure, becauſe many are op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, and more excluded from ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in the benefit. In the preſent caſe, if the one Party be the only exalted Ones, and the other trodden under foot, the damage will redound to the Proteſtant cauſe, and to the Church and Kingdom of <hi>England.</hi> For what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſome men think, this Church and Kingdom is concerned in the one, as well as in the other Party. In the ſame caſe, though one ſide ſhould riſe ſuddenly to a great height, yet their Eſtate would be more ſecure and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, if they held the way open and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure to thoſe of the other ſide, ſeeing they are willing to cloſe upon terms juſt and reaſonable.</p>
            <p>Moreover, thoſe Kingdoms, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170477:6"/>Common-wealths, and Societies of all kinds, which are of the largeſt Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, are of the greateſt potency. Now a comprehenſive Intereſt, that takes in vaſt multitudes, is indeed a large Foundation, and a Society that builds upon it, ſhall become great and mighty; but a contracted Intereſt, that draws all to a fewer number, is a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Foundation; and if it exclude many, that ſhould be taken in, it is too narrow for the Fabrick that ſhould reſt upon it. As a large houſe cannot be built upon a narrow foundation; ſo a great Kingdom, (ſuch as is the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>England,</hi>) and an ample Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, (ſuch as is that of the Proteſtant Religion,) cannot be built upon a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Intereſt.</p>
            <p>Let it be conſidered, that the adverſe Kingdom, to wit, the Papacy, is ample and powerful: Should not the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion, and the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> aim at enlargement, and length<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en their cords, to take within their line all thoſe that are intirely affected to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170477:7"/>them? Then might they ſend forth much more numerous Forces of able Champions againſt the Armies of Antichriſt: So ſhould this National Church become <hi>terrible as an Army with Banners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides thoſe reaſons for Unity, which concern all Kingdoms and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the like caſe, there is one rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon peculiar to this Kingdom, or rather to this Iſland of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ttain,</hi> which is a little world apart. It is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>able ſaying, which hath been taken up. <hi>That</hi> England <hi>is a mighty Arrival, that cannot dye, except it destroy it ſelf.</hi> God hath ſo ſea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed and placed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſland, that nothing but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it ſelf can hurt it. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction do not make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Country, and deſtroy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the hope of Forrein Enemies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> for ever cut off. Wherefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> s be the wiſedom of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther all dividing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liſh all partial Intereſts, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon Intereſt of <hi>England may</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> exalted.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:170477:7"/>
            <p>I am not ignorant that deſigns of Pacification between diſagreeing Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are liable to much ſuſpition, miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtruction, and hard cenſure; that the attempts of Reconcilers have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly proved fruitleſs, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times matter of diſreputation to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: and no marvel that ſuch croſs effects ſhould commonly follow ſuch attempts; for ſometimes they are made to reconcile light and darkneſs, the Temple of God and Idols. This was the way of a Great One, even a Prince in Learnings Empire, who would make an accord between the <hi>Auguſtane</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion and the Council of <hi>Trent;</hi> and alſo of a certain Romiſh Eccleſiaſtick, who would make the like accord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the ſaid Council, and the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> than which nothing could be more abſurd and vain; for it could be nothing elſe but a violent wreſting of thoſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees and Articles to a forced ſence, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the propriety of language, and the ſcope of the whole matter, and the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170477:8"/>apparent judgment of both Parties; and ſo it could never heal the breach: For if both Parties were drawn to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the ſame forms of Confeſſion, but with meanings ſo far diſtant from each other, as are the Doctrines of the Proteſtant, and Roman Churches, they would not really advance one ſtep the nearer to peace and concord.</p>
            <p>Such deſigns as theſe ſometimes proceed from lukewarmneſs or indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferency in Religion, and an underva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luing of main Truths, together with a contempt of godly Zeal, as a thing ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous and impertinent. And ſometimes they proceed from vaſtneſs of mind, whereby ſome through too great a ſence of their vaſt abilities, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to themſelves a Dictatorſhip in Religion, to approve or condemn, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit or reject, according to their own eſtimation of things; which is a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous kind of ambition, and (as a learned man ſpeaks) is to take up the Office of an Umpire between God and men. But many times ſuch a deſign
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170477:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>is ſet on foot with much craftineſs, for the undoing of one of the Parties, as it hath been undertaken by ſome Romiſh ſpirits, for the undermining of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Churches. A Divine of chief rank obſerves the arts and ſtratagems of ſome Popiſh Preachers, even of thoſe Orders that have been held moſt implacable, whereby far otherwiſe than the accuſtomed manner, they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuate the controverſies, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that too much rigor hath been uſed in ſome points, and in others too little ſincerity: yea, ſome Jeſuites went about making fair promiſes, yet in the mean time abating no point of the chief foundations of Papal Authority, which ſtanding firm, they knew that the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Conceſſions granted for a time might eaſily be drawn back, and the oppoſite rigors impoſed on thoſe that had been taken in the ſnare by a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended yielding to ſome reformation. <hi>Philip Melancthon</hi> (as the ſame Author obſerves) being a moſt Pious and Learned man, and zealous of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170477:9"/>peace, at firſt whilſt he conceived that ſome Reformation might be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for from a General Council, was free and forward in ſome points of yiel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Papiſts; but when he found that ſuch a benefit was neither hopeful nor poſſible, he teſtified by his writings how far diſtant he was from the aim of the Conciliators.</p>
            <p>But the Pacification here propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed is not by aggregating things incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent, nor by deviſing mongrel ways and opinions, made up out of both ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams, which can ſatisfie the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of neither Party; but by taking out of the way ſuch extreams on both ſides, as both may well ſpare and part with, being ſuch as are acknowledged no part of the Foundation, nor yet of divine Inſtitution, but mutable, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to times and occaſions, and therefore cannot be of that importance as to break unity amongſt brethren, that agree in the Doctrine of Faith, and the ſubſtance of Divine Worſhip. This deſired Union is grounded upon the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170477:9"/>Apoſtles Commandment, and the purſuing thereof is no other then the urging of St <hi>Pauls</hi> Doctrine through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole fourteenth Chapter to the Romans, That none judge or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe another about things indifferent, or Ceremonious Obſervances, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in as ſeveral men will abound in their own ſence, ſo it is meet that every one be perſwaded in his own mind concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his particular practice, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing be done with a doubting conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. His MAJESTIES Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom hath rightly comprehended this Matter in His Declaration touching <hi>Eccleſiastical Affairs,</hi> wherein He ſaith, —<hi>VVe are the rather induced to take this upon Us</hi> (that is, to give ſome deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination to the matters in difference) <hi>by finding upon a full Conference that VVe have had with the Learned men of ſeveral perſwaſions, that the miſchiefs under which both Church and State do at preſent ſuffer, do not reſult from any form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Doctrine or Concluſion which either Party maintains or avows, but from the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170477:10"/>paſsion, and appetite, and Intereſt of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons, which contract greater prejudice to each other by thoſe affections, then would naturally ariſe from their Opinions.</hi>— In old time there was a partition wall of legal Ceremonies and Ordinances raiſed up between Jews and Gentiles; but when the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of time was come, wherein God would make both Jews and Gentiles one in Chriſt, he was pleaſed to take down that partition wall which him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf had reared up. In theſe latter times there hath been a partition wall of mans building, namely, controverted muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Rites and forms of Religion, which have kept aſunder Chriſtians of the ſame Nation, and of the ſame Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Proteſtant Profeſſion: Both rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and charity pleads for the removing of theſe offences, that brethren may dwell together in Unity. And to tranſgreſs this rule of Charity, is not only to lay a yoke upon the necks of Chriſtians, but alſo to lay ſnares for their Conſciences.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:170477:10"/>
            <p>Nor will any defect in the State Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical inſue upon the removal of theſe matters in controverſie: for the points of Doctrine, Worſhip, and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline acknowledged by both Parties, are a ſufficient and ample Foundation for the edification and peace of the Church to reſt upon; for which we cannot have a fuller Teſtimony than what is given by His MAJESTY in His aforeſaid Declaration,—<hi>VVe muſt for the Honour of all thoſe of either Perſwaſion, with whom we have confered, Declare, That the Profeſsions and deſires of all for the advancement of Piety and true Godlineſs are the ſame, their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsions of zeal for the Peace of the Church the ſame, of affection and duty to Us the ſame; they all approve Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; they all approve a ſet Form of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy; and they all diſapprove and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like the ſin of Sacriledge, &amp; the alienation of the revenue of the Church. And if up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe excellent Foundations, in ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to which there is ſuch an Harmony of Affections, any Superſtructure ſhould be
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170477:11"/>raiſed to the ſhaking of theſe Foundations, and to the contracting and leſſening of the bleſſed gift of Charity, which is a vital part of Chriſtian Religion, VVe ſhall think Our Self very unfortunate, and even ſuſpect that VVe are defective in that adminiſtration of Government with which God hath entruſted Us.</hi>—Theſe His Majeſties Words I receive with much veneration; for they are a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Sentence in the Mouth of the King, and they fathom the depth of this grand buſineſs.</p>
            <p>It is therefore manifeſt, as from Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſo from His Majeſties Teſtimony, that thoſe unhappy diſcords do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult from any formed Doctrine or Concluſion, that either toucheth or borders upon the Foundation; and that excellent Foundations are contained in thoſe points, in ſubmiſſion to which there is found ſuch an Harmony of Affections; and conſequently, that the laying aſide of all the points in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, would not cauſe any defect in the State Eccleſiaſtical. What then
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170477:11"/>is the root of theſe miſchiefs of Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Is it the perpetual hatred between the ſeed of the Woman, and the ſeed of the Serpent? or is it an uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and froward ſpirit of oppoſition, by reaſon of irritated animoſity, and deep ſuſpition or jealouſie? or is it ſome temporary carnal Deſign?</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>It is firſt inquired, <hi>Whether the root hereof be the perpetual ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred between the ſeed of the Woman, and the ſeed of the Serpent?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Nothing is more certain from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and experience, then that a form of the true Religion may be with a kind of Zeal embraced, and the power thereof hated and impugned by the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. The Scribes and Phariſees were zealous and exact in the outward forms of the law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> yet their hatred of the power of that Religion appeared by their obſtinate rejecting and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170477:12"/>of Chriſt, and thoſe that believed on him. Many do embrace a form of the Chriſtian Verity in the general Doctrines, and in ſome plauſible yet ſuperficial practice: Nevertheleſs they cannot abide the genuine and ſpiritual explication and cloſe application of the ſame Verity, leading to the life and power thereof. Now if this were the true ſtate of the difference, that thoſe of the one perſwaſion only did urge the neceſſity of the New Birth, and of a holy and circumſpect walking in all Chriſtians, and to that end ſeek the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of ſuch a Miniſtry as (with bleſſed <hi>Paul</hi>) travels in birth, till Chriſt be formed in the Hearers, and ſuch as is quick and powerful, entring to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding of the ſoul and ſpirit, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers the ſecret rottenneſs, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroys the ſelf-confidence of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful heart, and drives the ſoul out of ſelf to draw it to Chriſt; ſuch a Miniſtry as is aſſiduous and inſtant in the diſpenſation of the word by inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, reproof and comfort, and in all
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170477:12"/>other parts of the Paſtoral duty, that as much as in it lies, it may preſent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man perfect in Chriſt: And if thoſe of the other perſwaſion account the urging of theſe things ſever fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, peeviſhneſs, pride, hypocriſie, affected ſingularity, and ſuppoſe the way to heaven common and eaſie, and accordingly ſeek the advancement of ſuch a Miniſtry that is more ſmooth and plauſible then ſearching and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, more ſlack and cold in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick diſpenſation of the Word, and in private admonition, indulging the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples corruptions, and generally tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizing with their carnal ſpirit; I ſay, if the caſe were ſo between them, I could proceed no further; for in ſuch a caſe to propoſe ways of Accommodation, were to make propoſals of Peace to Parties divided by an everlaſting en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity: but God forbid that the ſtate of the difference ſhould be ſo deplorable. We truſt that neither the one nor the other have ſo learned Chriſt as to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt a form of Godlineſs, and deny the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170477:13"/>power thereof: And that it is not or ought not to be ſo, and that it is on all hands diſavowed with deteſtation, we take it for a principle or ground-work whereon to bottom our whole deſign. The King Declares, <hi>That the Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and deſires of all thoſe of either per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, with whom he hath conferred, are the ſame for the advancement of Piety and true Godlineſs.</hi> Let the joynt purſuance of theſe profeſſions and deſires ſet both Parties agreed, eſpecially ſince His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty hath thus Declared in theſe graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous words,—<hi>Our purpoſe and reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is, and ſhall be, to promote the power of Godlineſs, to encourage the exerciſes of Religion both publique and private, and to take care that the Lords Day may be applied to holy exerciſes, without un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary divertiſements, and that inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, negligent, and ſcandalous Ministers may not be promoted in the Church.</hi>—</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:170477:13"/>
               <head>Is an uncharitable and froward ſpirit of oppoſition, by reaſon of irritated animoſity, and deep ſuſpition and jealouſie, the root of theſe diſcords?</head>
               <p>We fear indeed that too much tart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, if not bitterneſs of ſpirit, keeps the Breach open. Differences of long continuance and ſetled prejudices do choak the exerciſe of Charity. And the truth is, formerly the current of oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions ran along to aggravare theſe differences, and to exaſperate theſe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. Let us now at length take hold of the right means to ſtop this current of contention. Remove the occaſions, lay aſide controverted matters, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of there will be no miſs in the Church of God: Let forms of Worſhip and Government be ſo cut out, that they may not pinch and gall the conſciences of either Party, as it may be done by men of ſober and charitable judgments
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170477:14"/>without any impeachment of ſuch or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and decency, as agrees with the ſimplicity and ſpiritual Glory of Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel Adminiſtrations; ſo after a while the froward humor that worketh on both ſides, would ſpend and loſe it ſelf: Yea, I am perſwaded that ſome ſpirits now exulcerated through theſe diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, would not prove incurable or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable. After a little experience of ſuch proper healing remedies, both ſides will find themſelves brethren that had miſtaken one another, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken their common Intereſt.</p>
               <p>Moſt ſerious thoughts of heart have often led me to contemplate and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the peculiar calamity of the Church of God in theſe Dominions, that from time to time it hath been af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with the moſt unhappy kind of controverſies: for they come not neer the Foundation, nevertheleſs they are very pernicious and deſtructive. They conſiſt not ſo much in ſpeculation as practice, and particularly their imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate influence is upon the Churches
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170477:14"/>intereſt, and inevitably makes a breach in Church-Unity. For Eccleſiaſtical Offices, and Church Priviledges, and Communion of Worſhip both in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and latter times, have been inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with ſuch Forms and Rites and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther needleſs rigors, that the way there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto was kept ſhut againſt many that had received with the heart that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Faith which was once given to the Saints. Hence proceeded deſpiſing and judging one another, and deep cenſures, alienations and ſeparations, which will undoe any Society of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Profeſſion. The Papiſts not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their great boaſt of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, are much more divided within themſelves than any Proteſtants from each other; for the rent goes thorow the main Foundation of their Faith. With them the Head Corner-ſtone, or rather the adequate Foundation, is their Churches infalibility; but where to place this pretended infalibility, they can by no means agree: for upon the matter one half of them place it in the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170477:15"/>Pope, and the other in a General Council. If you ask, <hi>How then doth that vaſt Building hang together? How doth that</hi> Babyloniſh <hi>Kingdom ſtand?</hi> Surely they have the skill to make that great point of difference a matter of ſpeculation more then of practice, and they hold faſt two main practical things which do hold both in one; namely, the <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> under the Headſhip of the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the <hi>Maſs.</hi> They are all one both in Worſhip and Church-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and alſo in the whole body of Eccleſiaſticks, compacted by ſeveral joynts and ligaments under one Papal Head. Thus the children of this world are wiſe in their generation; and let the children of Light borrow this point of Wiſedom from them, which is to take care that our different opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons do not brangle our Church-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion and Eccleſiaſtical Politie. And in as much as Proteſtants have not that Popiſh way of quick diſpatch for all controverſies, which is to acquieſce in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170477:15"/>the Churches infalibility; but accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their Principles, they muſt ſeek their VVarrant from Scripture, by the help of the Churches directive, and their own diſcretive Judgment, the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly way for them to hold themſelves in the bond of Peace, is to avoid all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of things unneceſſary, in which it is exceeding difficult, or morally im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for all ſound Proteſtants to be of the ſame perſwaſion.</p>
               <p>Let us here take notice of another ſingular point of VViſedom, followed by the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> which was to ſhun, as a rock, the determining of ſuch Doctrines as were controverted among the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques; and according to this ſetled Rule the debates of that Council were governed: Oft times indeed there aroſe hot conteſts among the Divines about Scholaſtical niceties, the ſeveral Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Friars being therein paſſionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly addicted to their ſeveral opinions; but the Prelates, who alone had the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſive Voice, would always bring
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170477:16"/>things to a temper, and the Decrees were ſo framed, that the Opinions of neither Party were condemned. Let the Church of Chriſt mingle this Wiſedom of the Serpent with its dove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Innocency, to wit, not to urge with ſeverity things diſputed amongſt ſound and ſober Proteſtants. But it hath ſeemed good to ſome Proteſtants to walk by a contrary rule, to heighten differences between themſelves, and thoſe whom they called Puritanes, and to judge them irreconcileable, and to leſſen differences between themſelves and the Romaniſts, in order to a Paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication. We hope that this errour is or may be perceived by thoſe that have been inchanted into it. I am informed by a Writer of our Eccleſiaſtical Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, who is of the Epiſcopal per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, That an Epiſcopal Doctor of great note, and now a Biſhop, did within theſe few years uſe his utmoſt endeavours to gain upon the <hi>Sorbonists</hi> in <hi>Paris,</hi> and thereupon that he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied with them as far as he could do
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170477:16"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Chriſtian prudence, and with a ſafe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onſcience. Now the <hi>Sorboniſts</hi> are the moſt moderate Papiſts, and the ſaid Doctor is known to be far enough from the leaſt ſmatch of Puritaniſm; yet not any Accommodation could be heard of between them; but rather the contrary, even in the point of the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crypha.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seeing theſe things are ſo, one might wonder that any learned men, zealous of the Proteſtant Religion, ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main averſe from the true way of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty among diſagreeing Proteſtants, when the pacification between Proteſtants and Papiſts is become deſperate. One would conclude that Wiſe and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men could not be ſo overſeen, if there were not a deeper myſtery in this buſineſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Whereupon I paſs to a farther Inquiry, <hi>Whether the foment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of theſe diſcords do not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from a carnal deſign?</hi> And
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170477:17"/>ſhall argue even upon the caſe of a worldly Intereſt, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the way of ſevere Impoſing, or of moderate Condeſcending, be the more adviſable?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>If the ſettlement of the Churches Peace, by giving needful ſatisfaction and ſecurity to the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and the inlargement of the Churches In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, by taking in the multitudes of that denomination, be neglected in this diſcerning Age, we muſt needs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that the root of this diſſention goes deeper then paſſions, prejudices and miſ-apprehenſions, and that ſome car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and partial Intereſt is that root of bitterneſs that bears this gall and wormwood.</p>
               <p>Papiſts themſelves have noted, that the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> had rather abandon the hopes of regaining three Kingdoms to their pretended Catholique Church, then declare it lawful for the Engliſh Papiſts to take the Oath of Allegiance.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170477:17"/>When the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> was held, &amp; moſt of the Princes that ſent Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors to the Council were inſtant that ſome regard might be had of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, and their recovery endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by moderation and reformation; the Pope knowing that their return up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch tearms could never be hoped for, without the diminution of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue and Authority of his Court, judged it moſt neceſſary for the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of his pretended Apoſtolique See, to make the diviſion ſtrong and the Parties irreconcilcable, that thoſe Countries and People which continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in obededience to him might be kept intirely Popiſh.</p>
               <p>When men contend for the immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tability of mutable Orders, and ſtifly oppoſe the due regulation of things ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitant and exceſſive, and reſolve to give no ground for the gaining of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting brethren, it is not the love of Chriſt, but perverſe ſelf-love, and the love of the world that conſtrains them. Such intereſted perſons are never good
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170477:18"/>Counſellors for the publique weal.</p>
               <p>Now in as much as ſome particular carnal Intereſt is juſtly ſuſpected in the impetuous and obſtinate purſuance of the things in controverſie, we are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling here to make it a queſtion of Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and upon that account to make an addreſs to the Reaſon even of thoſe that are carried forth with greateſt vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence in favour of the Epiſcopal, and in oppoſition to the Presbyterian Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. All enterpriſes that have their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning in judgment and not in paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are directed to a certain end ſet up as a mark, and that end is not a buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs at rovers, but ſome particular ſteddy iſſue of things certainly or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably apprehended and expected: Wherefore let wiſe men conſider the mark whereat they level, and to what iſſue and ſtate of things their actions tend. Here is a numerous party, not of the dreggs and refuſe of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but of the judicious and ſerious part thereof: What will they do with them? and how will they order the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170477:18"/>matter concerning them? Would they deſtroy them? I ſolemnly profeſs that I abhor to think ſo by the generallity of the Epiſcopal perſwaſion: I would diſdain to mention ſuch an unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble impiety, were it not to ſhew the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate and abſurd proceedings of an unalterable oppoſition, as that it cannot drive to any formed end and iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue. That Proteſtants ſhould deſtroy Proteſtants for diſſenting in the point of Ceremonies, and ſole juriſdiction of Biſhops, is ſo dreadful a violation of Charity and common honeſty, that it is a moſt uncharitable and diſhoneſt thing to ſuppoſe it of them. What then? would they bear them down, or keep them under hard Conditions? Shall all perſons that cannot yield ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act obedience to Eccleſiaſtical injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons concerning all the parts of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy, and Ceremonies, be ſuſpended and deprived as formerly? Shall Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of this Judgment be caſt and kept out of Eccleſiaſtical preferment and imployment? Shall all private
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170477:19"/>conferences of godly peaceable Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, for mutual edification, be held unlawful Conventicles? It hath been thought by wiſe men to be againſt the Rules of Government to hold un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a rigid yoke a free people of ſuch a number and quality, and intermin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled in all eſtates and ranks, and inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mately conjoyned with all parts of the body Politique, that it is almoſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to exclude their Intereſt from a conſiderable ſhare in publique acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Beſides, is it for the ſervice of Chriſt, and the encreaſe of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom the Church, that ſo many able Divines ſhould be debarred the uſe of their Lords Talents, that ſo many la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious Miniſters ſhould ſit ſtill in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; that when Chriſt teacheth us to pray that the Lord would thruſt forth Labourers into his Harveſt, thoſe La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers ſhould be thruſt out of his har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt? Surely this would make a cry in the ears of the Lord of the Harveſt. Let me add this, 'Tis a hard matter to ſilence them that will preach virtually
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170477:19"/>in pious Conferences, whoſe occaſional and table diſcourſes will be a kind of Sermon.</p>
               <p>Let me offer a third way, Will they afford them liberty of Conſcience, and yet ſtave them off, as a divided Party, to ſtand alone in their Principles and Intereſt? Verily I cannot think it is in their heart ſo to do. What then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains but to prepare the way, and to make the path ſtraight for a ſolid and perfect cloſure, by laying aſide thoſe unneceſſary occaſions of ſtumbling.</p>
               <p>If the neglect of brotherly Pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation hold on, and the <hi>Hierarchy</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve upon their own advancement to the higheſt pitch, one may well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, That they make a full reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to wear out the Presbyterians, and to ſwallow up their Intereſt, conceiving they are able to effect it by degrees; and that greater changes then theſe have been wrought without much ado. And we confeſs indeed, that a great change in Religion was made by Qu. <hi>ELIZABETH</hi> without much
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170477:20"/>diſpute or difficulty: The alteration was not ſudden but gradual. <hi>Camden</hi> writes, that in the entrance of the Queens Raign, for a whole moneth and more, the Roman Religion ſtood as it did at the death of Queen <hi>MARY.</hi> On the 27. of <hi>December</hi> the Epiſtles and Goſpels, the Lords Prayer, Creed and Ten Commandements, together with the Letany, were read in the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Tongue. On the 22. of <hi>March</hi> the intire uſe of the Sacrament in both kindes was reſtored by Parliament. On the 24. of <hi>June</hi> the Sacrifice of the <hi>Maſs</hi> was aboliſhed, and the whole Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy reſtored into Engliſh. In <hi>July</hi> the Oath of Supremacy was given to the Biſhops: And in <hi>Auguſt</hi> Images were taken out of the Churches and broken or burnt. Why may not the <hi>Hierarchical</hi> Intereſt ſwallow up the <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> as eaſily as <hi>Proteſtantiſm</hi> prevailed over <hi>Popery?</hi> Surely I take theſe ſeveral caſes to be very different. And firſt, becauſe Queen <hi>ELIZA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BETH</hi> had this fundamental max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ime
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170477:20"/>as agreeable to her Conſcience and the Intereſt of Her State, to baniſh hence the exerciſe of the Roman Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. But our Gracious King in His Chriſtian Prudence and Compaſſion ſeeks the uniting of His Proteſtant Subjects, and the healing of their breaches by His Wiſe and Gracious condeſcentions already Declared. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, in the beginning of the Queens Raign the inferiour Clergy of this Kingdom univerſally appeared to be but lukewarm Papiſts, and many of them might be ſuppoſed to be Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants in heart, and the moſt of them very unlearned, and indifferent men in Religion. And a great part of the <hi>Hierarchy</hi> were not more Zealous than the reſt: For when at that time the Eccleſiaſtical Promotions in <hi>England</hi> were numbred above nine thouſand four hundred in all, there were not more then fourſcore Rectors of Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, fifty Prebendaries, fifteen Heads of Colledges, twelve Arch-Deacons, twelve Deans, ſix Abbots and Abbeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170477:21"/>and fourteen Biſhops that refuſed the Oath of Supremacy. Alſo the Engliſh Service was ſo prepared that it might be no abomination to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, no poſitive thing therein occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring repugnant to their Doctrine; for which cauſe they frequented the ſame for the firſt ten years; and the Pope did not in many years ſend forth his thunder &amp; lightning againſt the Queen. And Popery being in ſubſtance a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion contrary to what was publickly profeſſed, had no advantage for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe by publick Preaching, or Books publickly allowed. All theſe accidents did help forward to an abſolute ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Proteſtant Religion. But we may find the ſtate of things far o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe in point of diſpoſition or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination toward the Dominion of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Prelacy, and the rigorous im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Ceremonies, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpation of the Diſſenting Party: For there are now in <hi>England</hi> thouſands of Miniſters diſ-ſatisfied in the <hi>Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> who are all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petently
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170477:21"/>and many of them eminently learned. They are not generally of light ſpirits, but ſteddy and well reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and tenderly affected touching their ſpiritual liberties. The way which in ſcorn is called Puritaniſm, is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Religion in ſubſtance than Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtantiſm, but the very ſame, or one branch thereof diſtinguiſhed from the other by an accidental difference. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant and Puritane Doctrine and Worſhip, all men may know to be the ſame for ſubſtance; and Puritaniſm will grow up with Proteſtantiſm, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all oppoſition, as I have manifeſted in the former diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>Commonly thoſe people who try all Doctrines by Scripture, and are ſway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more by its Authority than by the Ordinances and Cuſtoms of men, do much heſitate and ſtagger concerning the ſole Juriſdiction of Biſhops, the pomp of the <hi>Hierarchy,</hi> and ſacred my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Ceremonies of Humane Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And therefore let the Epiſcopal Party never look to be rid of theſe dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170477:22"/>till they remove the matters in Queſtion, whereat a knowing peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are always ready to ſtumble.</p>
               <p>Neither in theſe times are the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians ſo hateful a generation as ſome would have them: They are odious to none but thoſe to whom they were ever odious, or elſe to ſuch Ignorants as follow the Cry, and ſpeak evil of they know not what. They have had no conſiderable loſs of their number by revolt; and what ever comes to paſs, they think never the worſe of their main Cauſe, which I have expreſſed in the character given of them: And if ſome or many of them have a liberty in their own judgments touching con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, yet that Conformity will not ſtrengthen the deſigns of thoſe Prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts that are moſt rigid in ſuch impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and ſeek to tread down the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians. It was a notable queſtion which a <hi>Carthaginian</hi> Senator put to <hi>Hanibal</hi>'s Agents, after the great over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw given to the <hi>Romans</hi> at <hi>Canna.</hi> When they had magnified <hi>Hanibal</hi>'s
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170477:22"/>great Atchievements, <hi>Hanno</hi> asked them, <hi>Whether any of the</hi> Romans <hi>had come to demand Peace; and whether any Town of the Latines, or any of their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonies had yet rebelled againſt the Romans?</hi> The Agents denying the one and the other, <hi>Hanno</hi> replied, <hi>Then is the War as intire yet as at the firſt.</hi> I apply this, to ſhew how eaſily men miſtake the progreſs of their own affairs, and think themſelves to be ready for a triumph, when indeed they have gotten little, and the ſtate of the controverſie is ſtill as intire and firm as ever.</p>
               <p>Hitherto I have aſſerted <hi>the Interest of the Univerſality in oppoſition to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of a partial Intereſt:</hi> I have endeavoured to make it manifeſt, <hi>That the ſeveral Parties by a mutual yielding and waving their partial Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, may be united to promote the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of the Univerſality:</hi> for I have layd theſe ground-works, to wit, <hi>That the breach is not kept open by any formed Doctrine or Concluſion of either Party,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170477:23"/>nor (as I trust) by the ſpirit of everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting enmity; but either by a humour of oppoſition, that may be qualified and ſubdued, or by ſome carnal d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſign, which may and muſt be denied when its errour and danger is diſcovered.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the remainder of this Diſcourſe I am to ſhew, <hi>That the Presbyterians are fit and worthy to be imbodied with the whole number of the good people of</hi> England; in the next place <hi>to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the Union by ſeveral Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;</hi> and then <hi>to remove certain impediments, and to argue from the particular Concernments of the King, of the Nobility and Gentry, and of the Epiſcopal Clergy;</hi> and laſtly, <hi>to offer ſome few eſſays concerning the paths of Peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was ſometimes conſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the weakneſs of ſome and the malice of others, to boaſt on his own behalf, and to Apologize again and again for ſpeaking as a fool: I truſt
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170477:23"/>therefore that wiſe men will bear with that unto which the like neceſſity com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels me, on the behalf of the people that are now denominated Presbyterian. In eſtimating the numbers of this perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, it is not the right way to go by the Poll throughout all ſorts promiſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly; but to take a ſurvey of the intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent and active ſort of the people, and in that ſort to compare their number with others. Howbeit in any way of reckoning ſuppoſe them the leſſer, yet they may be found a balancing num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. But I am willing to paſs from number to weight. They that will not acknowledge them to be ſincere, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny them to be ſerious perſons; they that will not acknowledg them to be ſober in their judgments, cannot deny them to be ſober in their conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations. But we know they are both ſerious, and ſincere, and ſober, as well in Religion as in Morality: and a few ſober people are more valuable, both for Religious and Civil concernments, than a multitude of diſſolute or vain
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170477:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>and empty perſons. One ſerious ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional man will carry more in fit op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities, than al the vapourers in the neighbourhood. Thoſe that are ill af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected to the Presbyterians commonly deſpiſe them as an unlearned dull ſort of men knowing nothing. Truly we will not herein boaſt beyond our line, nor magnifie thoſe of our own perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, in derogation to any others; but we think that this diſparagement is caſt upon them becauſe they are common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly no vapourers: Surely they have amongſt them both Divines and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, who do not uſe to turn their backs upon gainſayers, but have been and will be ready to render a reaſon of their judgment and practice to any that ſhall demand it of them.</p>
               <p>We do not envy the learning of any Epiſcopal Divines, but gladly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it, and deſire to partake in the benefit of it, and wiſh that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever gift is received by any, may be more and more ſerviceable to the Church of God: Neither are they an
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170477:24"/>ignoble abject ſort; it hath not at all appeared that they have degenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the Engliſh Virtue and Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour. They have for common tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility and ſafety cloſed with the firſt opportunity for a general accord, and ſo have knowingly made way for the reviving of the other Party, ſuppoſing that the former enmity would ceaſe. And they had reaſon to hope, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſt the joy of the Nation, they ſhould not be left in ſadneſs. The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent interruption and check given to this expected reconciliation, we attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to the hurry of mens minds upon this great and unexexpected change, by which it happeneth that they ſcarce know where they are, and hardly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain themſelves within due bounds. But we truſt that theſe paſſions will be over &amp; the ſpirits of all will ſettle in a calm and good temper. Hitherto the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions may paſs for the effects of paſſion, not of inveterate malice, wherefore, <hi>dum res est integra,</hi> let ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond thoughts be milder. A quick paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170477:25"/>of Count <hi>Oli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>res</hi> touching the right way of Accommodation, may be pertinent to this buſineſs. Our late Soveraign, when Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> being in the Spaniſh Court in purſuance of the marriage with the <hi>Infanta</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> and the Negotiation being clogged with many interruptions, diſcontents and jealouſies, and all being like to fall aſunder, <hi>Olivares</hi> whether in humour or earneſt propounded theſe three ways; The firſt, <hi>That Prince</hi> Charles <hi>ſhould become a Catholique;</hi> The ſecond, <hi>That the</hi> Infanta <hi>ſhould be delivered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him upon the former ſecurity without further Condition;</hi> The third was, <hi>To bind him as faſt as they could, and not to truſt him with any thing.</hi> Of theſe three ways, he ſaid, the two former were good; but the laſt was a bad one. In like manner might a diſcerning Prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt reſolve, that there be three ways of bringing theſe diſputes to an iſſue; The firſt, <hi>That the Presbyterians ſhould vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily become Epiſcopal, and thorowly conformable;</hi> The ſecond, <hi>That the way
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170477:25"/>of brotherly accord ſhould be held open and ſecure to them by an equal Accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation;</hi> The third, <hi>That they be truſted in nothing, but bound up fast by the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Condition that can be impoſed.</hi> Of theſe three ways let him conclude with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to his own intereſt, that the two former are good, but the laſt very bad.</p>
               <p>Much partiality and prejudice hath gotten the ſway in thoſe men that ſpeak and act, as if there were cauſe to fear none, to curbe none, to provide reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies againſt none but Presbyterians: Was <hi>England</hi> acquainted with no trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, or infeſted with no inteſtine broyls before this kind of men aroſe? Are theſe the proper Enemies of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land?</hi> Let them know, that the true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtine Enemies of any State are thoſe within it, that depend upon Forreign Intereſts, and on whom Forreign States have influence.</p>
               <p>A great Stateſ-man makes it one fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental maxime of Queen <hi>ELI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ZABETH</hi> to baniſh hence the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170477:26"/>of the Roman Religion, becauſe it was the only means to break all the plots of the Spaniards, who under this pretext did here foment Rebellion. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame ground the Law baniſheth Popiſh Prieſts, that Forreign influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces might not diſtemper this Kingdom: But the Presbyterians can have no temptation to tamper with Forreign Combinations; for their Intereſt is preciſely and perfectly Proteſtant, and for their unreconcilableneſs to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> their greateſt adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries will bear them witneſs: And when ever this Land ſhall have need of help againſt its chiefeſt Enemies, they will be found ſo true to the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of <hi>England,</hi> as none more, and conſequently muſt and will be intereſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in its defence. Wherefore let <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> have regard to thoſe that muſt be her faſt friends, not only for good will, but alſo for perpetual neceſſity.</p>
               <p>Moreover, a wiſe State is buſie in finding out, but not in making Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. Who can produce one ſolid
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170477:26"/>reaſon, that renders this Party Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the Government, or the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Governing? They are lovers of Monarchy, and of the Royal Family. From neither of theſe have they any cauſe of diſtruſt or diſ-ſatisfaction. They have nothing to hold in deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to His Majeſties Authority, ſafety, or benefit; and His Majeſty hath no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to hold that ſtands in oppoſition to their ſecurity. There have been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed unhappy differences; but whence proceeding? Not from any thing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſecal to His Majeſties Government or to their condition; but from things very remote from the Intereſt of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty. The Kings Affairs do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Him to extend Favour and Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency to them, as to any other of His Subjects; and His Condeſcention to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them will work as happy effects to His ſatisfaction.</p>
               <p>Some men reſolving in all things to detract from the Presbyterians, have ſaid, That they promoted the Kings Return, not out of good will to His
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170477:27"/>Majeſty, or a love of Order and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; but out of fear of being deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Phanaticks. Upon the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of this ſurmiſe, and the evil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign thereof, I am willing to debate this Queſtion,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whether the Presbyterians cloſure with the King in all avowed ſubjection and ſervice be ſincere and ſolid, that His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty may ſafely confide in them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The pretended reaſon of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſincerity ſeems to me to add much to their reputation in that behalf: For if the Phanaticks would deſtroy them, it is manifeſt that they are none of them. Panaticks would not deſtroy them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves willingly. The ſeveral various Sects will wrangle with each other in verbal conteſts; but they never know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly plotted or banded againſt each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon the account of their different Opinions, but did all unite in one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Principle of pretended liberty of Conſcience, and in one common cauſe of Univerſal Toleration. Be it alſo granted, that ſelf-preſervation enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170477:27"/>the Presbyterians by any means to obviate and overturn the deſigns of the Sectaries, it ſhews that the Sectarian Intereſt and theirs are inconſiſtent, as alſo that they are not unreconcilable to the Epiſcopal part of Proteſtants; and that they had pacifick inclinations, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to put a period to theſe contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Let men ſurmiſe the worſt they can of their intentions in declaring for the King; yet in as much as they had a choice before them, to turn this way or that way, it is evident they would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take themſelves to that way that had the leſſer evil and the fairer ſhew of good. And could any think that they would knowingly make a choice of that which ſhould deſtroy their juſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty: wherefore were it no more than this, it might gain them ſome regard, for that they hoped for ſome good in this way, when they could hope for none at all from the wilde ways and fancies of Phanaticks: But the truth is, they turned not to a leſſer evil, but to a thing in it ſelf deſirable; for it was a
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170477:28"/>clear caſe to men of ſound minds and ſober Principles, that there was no way to lead us out of that wilderneſs where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we wandred, but the uniting of all ſound and ſober Proteſtants in things wherein all agree, and a mutual for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance in things not neceſſary to peace and edification. The Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians knew their ſingle Intereſt would not ſettle the Nation: And the Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palians may know as well that their ſingle Intereſt will prove deficient. In ſuch a caſe what well-minded perſons affecting the peace of the Church and Kingdom would not promote the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Royal Family, that the King, in whom alone the whole Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on can ſettle, may pare off the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities of particular partial Intereſts, and make a Union in the general Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of the Proteſtant Religion, and of Great <hi>Brittain?</hi> This was the ſcope of the Presbyterian deſign in that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular: And as touching their cordial affection to His Majeſties Perſon and Government, we have their own more
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170477:28"/>affectionate and ſolemn profeſſions for it, which are graciouſly owned by His Majeſty. And if any perſiſt to gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay thoſe expreſſions, ſeeing they are not ſearchers of hearts, it lies upon them to prove this pretended diſaffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction by ſomthing diſcernable in the outward behaviour. But ſuppoſe that a peoples Conſcience and good incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and diſpoſition be called into queſtion, yet this is a maxime unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionable, <hi>That the main ground of ſure and constant benevolence between Prince and People, is a firm perſwaſion, that they are the mutual Intereſt of each other.</hi> His Majeſties Royal Perſon and His Princely Virtues are amiable to us; He is a Crown of Glory to the Engliſh Nation: But that which got the maſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry over all difficulties, in reſtoring Him to His Dominions, was an undoubted knowledge that the Nations Intereſt was bound up in Him our indubitable Sovereign Lord. There is a neceſſity of meer compulſion that drives the unwilling, and there is a neceſſity of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170477:29"/>Intereſt that draws a willing people: When this latter neceſſity doth bring a Prince and People together, ingenuous minds will turn this neceſsity into a virtue; and ſo the joyning of Intereſts draws after it the joyning of hearts. The Presbyterians enjoying the ſame protection and benefit with other ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Proteſtants and Loyal Subjects, will ſee no other probable nor poſſible way of repoſe and ſafety but under His Majeſties happy Government. It is not therefore a neceſſity of preſent force, but of conſtant Intereſt, which is here commended, as ſo great a bond of loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, and which Princes uſe to take for their beſt ſecurity. The wiſeſt way is, not to reject and ſlight a party that are brought to hand, and made for a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces Intereſt, upon a ſuſpition that they may prove inconſtant; but to uſe the known means of preventing ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancy as is pretended, and to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt that regard to their encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and ſatisfaction, as that they may reſt aſſured, that their own and the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170477:29"/>publick peace do run in the ſame chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>From the Reaſons aforegoing I conclude, <hi>That the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians are ſit and worthy to be imbodied with the whole num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the good People of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. I proceed to perſwade this Union by ſeveral Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>England</hi> hath indured conflicts of almoſt twenty years by Wars, Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Commotions, and manifold chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; it was abaſed, enfeebled, and brought very low; all which do ſhew that ſome great diſtemper had taken hold of this Body Politique, before theſe things could break forth: There is at length by the late Revolution a providential offer of reſt and peace. After thoſe ſad conflicts, and this hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py offer of Providence, ſhall the ſeeds
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170477:30"/>of diſcord lodge perpetually in this Land? I fear paſsions of bitterneſs are too ready to ſtir and provoke. Take away this fewel of ſtrife, the urging of things to uphold diſtinctions of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Whileſt things are at ſuch a paſs, animoſities will ariſe upon every occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; diſcontents and quarrels will be ready to break forth in every Town and Pariſh, and almoſt in all mixed companies and occaſional Meetings. But let the propounded Accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be accepted and eſtabliſhed, and the former mutual injuries will paſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to forgetfulneſs, and perſons former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly engaged againſt each other, will be able to look one another in the face without provocation and new quarrels. Where is our Charity and regard to publick tranquillity, if we reject the ſure and only means of Concord?</p>
               <p>Uniformity in Religion is beautiful and amiable; but we ought to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der not only what is deſirable, but what is attainable. There have been, are, and always will be ſuch points as
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170477:30"/>the Apoſtle tearms <hi>doubtful diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> When the ſeverity of Laws and Canons inforce external Uniformity in things of this nature, it exerciſeth a tyranny over mens judgments, and holds them in a ſervile condition, that they are not free, but captivated to the Authority of men, or ſuppreſſed from making a due ſearch into matters of Religion; yea, this thraldom will ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitably reach to things of an higher nature, even the vital parts of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity. That ſervile Principle which hath the heart of Popery in it, muſt be introduced, to wit, that the Laity ſhould not ſearch the Scriptures, nor try the Doctrines delivered, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſce in what their Teachers ſay, without the Exerciſe of their own rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or judgment of diſcretion. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon will follow groſs ignorance and ſupine careleſneſs in the things of God, and in thoſe that any whit mind Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion (which is the beſt of the matter) a blind devotion: And a people rude and ſervile in Religion, will be rude
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170477:31"/>and diſſolute in Converſation, as we ſee in Popiſh Countries, and in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where ſpiritual tyranny prevaileth. This is ſo great an evil that it cannot be countervailed by all the imaginable benefit of Uniformity: And the truth is, all profitable Uniformity is mingled with ſobriety, and ſtands not in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diviſible point, but admits a latitude, and by a little variety in matters of leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer moment, becomes more graceful, becauſe it is more unſtrained and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected.</p>
               <p>It is a chief point of knowledge in thoſe whoſe work it is to mould and manage a Nation according to any order of things, to underſtand what is the temper of the people, what Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples poſſeſs and govern them, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Parties of them, and to what paſs things are already brought among them.</p>
               <p>Thoſe who duly obſerve and regard the diſpoſition and preſent State of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> and the principles and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the ſeveral conſiderable Parties,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170477:31"/>will be able to give the beſt advice for a happy ſettlement: For ſuch a courſe as is wiſely and ſuccesfully taken in one Nation, may in the like buſineſs prove unfortunate in another Nation, or in the ſame at another time. A State may probably root out ſuch opinions as it conceives to be heterodox and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convenient, by uſing great ſeverity in the beginning, when the opinions are but newly ſowed in mens minds, and the people are of ſuch a nature, as to abhor dangers, and aim to live ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and when the Nation in general is devoted to the ancient cuſtoms of their fore-fathers. But the ſame courſe may not be taken when the opinions have been deeply rooted and far ſpread, by long continuance, in a Nation of a free ſpirit, and zealous; and the generali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of thoſe, that in a Law-ſence are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Cives,</hi> do not deteſt them. At this day <hi>England</hi> affords a multitude of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopal Zealots, and a multitude of Presbyterian Zealots, ballancing the former; and between theſe two there
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170477:32"/>lye a more indifferent ſort of people, whereof a great number care for none of theſe things; but others are more intelligent and conſiderate; and theſe ſeem to approve ſome things, and again to diſapprove ſome things on either ſide: As far as I have obſerved the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different ſort of men do accord with the Epiſcopal way in affecting the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer Book; and thoſe among them, that are of any reckoning for worth or honeſty, do alſo according to the Presbyterian way, affect the conſtant preaching of the Word, and the reſidency of Miniſters in their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochial Charges, and diſaffect plura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Benefices. Knowledge hath ſo encreaſed that the people in general will more obſerve their Teachers Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and converſation; and the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinencies of the one, and the irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularities of the other ſhall not paſs without noting. The inſufficient, idle, and ſcandalous will fall into contempt, and be ſlighted by the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. The profanation of the Lords
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170477:32"/>Day by open ſports and paſtimes is by the Civil part of the Nation account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſcandalous. Furthermore, the preſent Age being more diſcerning, all ſorts affect a greater liberty of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Diſcourſe then hath been uſed in former times. Whereupon the State of this Kingdom requires a temper or medium between two ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treams, to wit <hi>medium abnegationis,</hi> in thoſe unneceſſary things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in no accord can be expected between the Parties, by aboliſhing, or not injoyning them, and <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium participationis,</hi> in things neceſſary to Order and Government, wherein the moderate of both Parties do eaſily comply with each other. When the State like a prudent Mother, not led by the paſſions of her angry Children, ſhal not ingage in their quarrels on this or that ſide, but ſettle ſuch a tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for their common good, love and peace may enſue between the Parties, though difference of judgment ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains. When the Nation ſhall not
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170477:33"/>eſpouſe to it ſelf the intereſt of a party, but intirely reſerve it ſelf for the good of the Univerſality, thoſe hot diſputes and conteſts will of themſelves fall to the ground; and men of different judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments will be leſs fond of their own opinions, when they obſerve that the State doth not judge its happineſs to reſt upon any of them, and that the welfare of the Church and Kingdom conſiſts without them.</p>
               <p>This Kingdom after the removing of foundations, is by a marvellous turn re-eſtabliſhed upon its ancient baſis. And verily that which hath wrought the change will ſettle it; that which hath brought ſuch things to paſs, will keep them where they are, if we do not overlook and ſleight it. And what was it but the conſent of the univerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, the Vote of all <hi>England?</hi> This did produce an univerſal motion, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding vehement, but not violent: For it was not againſt, but according to nature. All things having been out of
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170477:33"/>place, and held in a ſtate preternatural, when the force was taken off, moved to their center and place of reſt, to wit, the ancient fundamental conſtitution. And for this cauſe the change was not terrible, but calm, kindly and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bloody: Now as that natural incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, which carries things to their reſting place, will keep them there, until by violence they are forced thence; ſo this conſent of the univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſality, which produced a kindly mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all things to ſettle in their own place and order upon the right foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, will keep them there, until ſuch external force ſhall come, as can break and diſſipate the univerſality. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeing this great revolution hath not happened by the prevailing force of one Party, but by the unſtrained motion of all <hi>England,</hi> what reaſon is there that one Party ſhould thruſt the other out of its due place of reſt upon the common Foundation? When com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon conſent hath laid this excellent Foundation of peace and quietneſs, let
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170477:34"/>not the Superſtructure of particular unneceſſary forms, caſt off ſome as a divided and rejected Party; but let that which hath made peace keep peace; which by Gods help it will ſurely do, if timely obſerved and followed.</p>
               <p>We cannot gainſay but the compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of theſe differences hath much dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty, and requires much prudence, care and patience in thoſe that are at the helm of Government: Nevertheleſs it may be effected, if the judicious on both ſides will give conſent; and they will give conſent, if they have a ſingle aim to procure the peace of Gods Church, and the increaſe thereof, and particularly the increaſe and ſtability of Proteſtant Religion, Suppoſe the <hi>Roman, Grecian, Armenian, Ethiopick,</hi> together with all the Proteſtant Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, yea and the whole Chriſtian world might be drawn into one Church-Communion and Order, upon as eaſie tearms as Engliſh Prelatiſts and Presbyterians may, if they have a heart to it, were it not prodigious unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tableneſs
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170477:34"/>and fury of oppoſition to withſtand it? As all the Lovers of Chriſtianiſm would purſue the Union of all Chriſtian Churches, upon ſuch tearms, ſo ſhould all the Lovers of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtantiſm purſue the Union of all Proteſtant Churches, ſeeing the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines wherein they harmoniouſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree will enable them to keep <hi>the Unity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace,</hi> if the heart be not oppoſite to the power of thoſe profeſſed Doctrines. To heal the wounds of the Proteſtant Cauſe, how glorious is it? But to refuſe and withſtand this healing, how doth it cauſe the Popiſh faction to glory a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us? <hi>Let not our adverſaries re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, nor the uncircumciſed glory in our ſhame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We have the examples of Chriſtian Princes, even thoſe of the Roman Faith, who would gladly have made up breaches in Religion among their people, by yielding in things of great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er moment in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> then any of the points in queſtion are
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170477:35"/>among diſagreeing Proteſtants. In the Council of <hi>Trent, Ferdinand</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, and <hi>Maximilian</hi> his ſon King of the Romans, and the French King, and the Duke of <hi>Bavaria</hi> made it their buſineſs by their Embaſſadors, for qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eting of their Dominions, that the Communion of the Sacrament in both kinds, the Marriage of Prieſts, and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Service in the vulgar tongue might be allowed. Theſe things are of greater importance among the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, then the things now in queſtion are among the Proteſtants of either per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, if we judge by their declared Opinions, and not by ſome hidden de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign: And thoſe forenamed Princes would ſurely have taken that way for uniting their people, had their power been independent in matter of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but having dependance upon the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> they could do nothing without the Authority either of the Pope or the Council; from either of which they perceived after much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, that ſuch Reformation could
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170477:35"/>not be hoped for. Moreover thoſe Princes being of the Roman Faith, had a fairer pretence according to Popiſh Principles, to cruſh the diſſenting Part of their Subjects, by laying Hereſie to their charge, and ſo in time to root them out, then any Proteſtant State can have to extirpate the Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. Likewiſe the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the V. after his great Atchievements, deſigning to eſtabliſh an intire Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in Germany, conceived that his way was to unite the German Nation in point of Religion, by a kind of refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation or Accommodation; for which he laboured ſo much in procuring and upholding the <hi>Trent</hi>-Council; until at length diſpairing of his Sons ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Empire, he laid aſide all thoughts of reſtoring the ancient Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in <hi>Germany,</hi> and by conſequence all care of the Council, though he continued many years after in the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Authority.</p>
               <p>Now though all theſe Princes were deceived in expecting ſuch a Union by
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170477:36"/>means of that Council, which by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of divers and important Intereſts of Princes and Prelates, could not poſſibly have ſuch an end as was by ſome of them deſired; yet herein they took not their aim amiſs, that the re-uniting of their broken people, by uſing a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and Accommodation, was the beſt way to keep their Eſtates intire.</p>
               <p>I am the more importunate in preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing home the motion of brotherly A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, conſidering the time, which may be the only time: For the preſent condition of theſe Affairs ſeem like to the ſtate of a ſick body, which Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans call a <hi>Criſis,</hi> when nature and the diſeaſe are in the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the conflict, to carry it for life or death. Peace and Concord in Religion ſeems now to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to its <hi>Criſis,</hi> whether it ſhall prevail and live, or dye and fail for ever: It may juſtly be feared that the time is now or never: For if after ſo long and ſad diviſions and the calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous effects thereof, an implacable ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſhall be ſeen to bear ſway in this
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170477:36"/>time of reſtauration and expected uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it may beget a deſpair of all future reconciliation. If after ſuch and ſo long calamities, all the concurring circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the late Revolution will not incline mens hearts to Peace, what will do it? This is a day of gracious Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. <hi>Happy</hi> England, <hi>if in this its day it knows the things that belong to its Peace!</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Having preſſed the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion by theſe Arguments, I proceed to remove certain impediments.</head>
               <p>One great impediment is an errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous judgment touching the times fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going the late wars. For as much as great and manifold diſtempers have happened and continued in this Land ſince the beginning of theſe troubles, the defects of former times are quite forgotten, as it commonly comes to paſs, that latter miſeries, if drawn out to any length, do drown the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berance
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170477:37"/>of by-paſt evils; but he who diſcerns only things at hand, and not affar off, is purblind. I abhor to take upon me the defence of our late di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted times, the diſtempers thereof I would not in any wiſe palliate. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs let this be noted, diſtempers have their times of breeding as well as of breaking forth. Certainly that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Tempeſt, which ſucceeded the long Calm in this Nation, had its time of gathering in the Clouds. To heal the ſymptomes of a diſeaſe, its rooted cauſe being neglected, is but a pallia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive cure. To take away the irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larities of theſe latter times, and not to inquire into the former cauſes, is to hide, but not to heal the maladies of this Kingdom.</p>
               <p>Another errour which turns away mens eyes from beholding the true ſtate of their own affairs, is a contempt of the diſſenting Party, and of their Opinions, as ſilly and irrational; with which is joyned a vain conceit, that the whole Party with their Opinions
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170477:37"/>would ſoon fall to the ground, if a few turbulent and factious ſpirits (as they pretend) were taken out of the way. This makes men to bear down their oppoſites more with ſcorn and contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely, then with any temperate and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid reaſoning. This makes men wilful, precipitate, unmerciful, and puts them forward by rigid injunctions and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere inquiſitions to ſuppreſs thoſe with whom they might walk in one way, if they themſelves did walk in love: But there is as little of Reaſon as Religion in this ſelf-admiring humour. It is the part of weak and ſelfiſh minds to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract Religion to certain modes and forms which ſtand not by Divine Right; but by the wills of men, and which are of little efficacy, and very diſputable, and if ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed lawful, ought to be governed by the rule of Charity. To think that none is a good Chriſtian, a ſound Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, a fit miniſter that cannot ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to ſuch modes and forms, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from a narrow and ignoble
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170477:38"/>judgment. It is alſo as much pride as weakneſs to contemn the ſetled way of a knowing and ſerious people, ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in their Principles and practices, as if they were worthy of no regard, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they diſſent in ſome points which in themſelves are of little moment. This is for men to think, that they only are the people, and that wiſdom ſhall dye with them. Noble and high ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities and judgments of a large and deep reach, do know they cannot ſquare the world by the narrow compaſs of thoſe conceived Principles that have poſſeſſed and ſeaſoned their own minds: But they look alſo without themſelves, rightly judging, that as they have their own peculiar Notions, ſo another ſort have theirs, and that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers men are carried divers ways, as they are led by natural temper, cuſtom, education, or ſtudious inquiries. They know likewiſe that there is no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining of all minds to one perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, without imbaſing their judgments to perfect ſlavery, which we ſee put in
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170477:38"/>practice in the Antichriſtian Kingdom of the Papacy: Whereupon men of vaſteſt parts and learning, and of true nobleneſs of judgment have been ever favourable to thoſe which diſſented only in ſuch opinions, as amongſt wiſe and ſober men are not with one conſent determined, unleſs their peculiar Intereſt were bound up in thoſe Opinions: For this noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of judgment, which natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inclines to allow ones ſelf and others this righteous liberty, is ſometimes dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven back and ſtreightned by politique Intereſts. Verily a judgment truly noble is truly Catholique; and true Catholiciſm is moſt contrary to that which is ſo called by pretended Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques: For it is to maintain Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Concord with all Chriſtians, as far as they hold Chriſt the Head.</p>
               <p>It is incident to ruling men to cheriſh the paſſion of indignation againſt the diſſenting Party. Hence ariſeth a great perturbation of judgment: For by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the dominion of this paſſion,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170477:39"/>when diſſenters modeſtly aſſert their Principles, and do not inſtantly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply as much as is expected, it is taken for petulancy and peeviſhneſs. When ſome degree of forwardneſs breaks forth, it is encountred with that ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity which hazards the undoing of the weak Part, that ſhould and might be healed: And their diſ-ſatisfaction is judged the effect of incurable pride and malice. This perturbation of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment begets a great diſtemper in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Councils. Wherefore let per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons bearing Rule watch over this dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous paſſion, and dread its tyranny. Firſt, let not perverſneſs be always im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to the non-compliances of the inferiour Party. God hath put it into the Kings heart to extend compaſsion to multitudes of His Loyal Subjects, in taking off the rigour of ſundry impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions in matters Eccleſiaſtical; and they think it good to make uſe of thoſe His Majeſties Conceſſions, without the prejudice of any part of Religion, or of order and decency in the Church.
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170477:39"/>Others that ſhould have helped for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards His Majeſties deſign of Peace, are offended, ſaying, The Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians yield in nothing, the late indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence hath made them more reſolved againſt all points of Conformity; But why ſhould their eye be evil becauſe His Majeſties eye is good? Have the Presbyterians abated nothing, when, for peace ſake they have declared a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs to part with the Presbyterian platform of Church-Government, which is uſed in other Reformed Churches, and to ſubmit to a regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Epiſcopacy; as alſo to wave the Directory for Worſhip, and to accept a Reformed Liturgy? Indifferent men would judge that this is a good ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance towards peace, and that a cloſure is hereby really intended. But what have the Prelatiſts done in teſtimony of their moderation? Have they deſiſted from the uſe of any one of the former Ceremonies, even ſuch as be not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned by any Law or Canon? Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſome of the Presbyterians (be they
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170477:40"/>few or many) do as yet forbear the us ſing of ſome forms, which they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend not ſimply unlawful; perhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome reaſon of ſcandal may cauſe this forbearance; otherwiſe to the judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous they might ſeem to contradict their own Principles, out of ſervile fear, or for worldly ends; and the malicious might take occaſion, though none were given, to reproach them for tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porizing. Now it concerns Chriſts Miniſters to prevent, what in them lies, not only a juſt, but even an unjuſt and cauſeleſs contempt of their Miniſtry. Beſides, they are not willing that ſome perſons of good affections, but weaker judgments, ſhould take offence at their early and eaſie compliance, and ſo fall into down-right ſeparation. The Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians attend a good Reformation, and all neceſſary inlargement that may encompaſs and gather together in one all that are of ſound belief and good life, who have been ſo long ſcattered abroad. Nothing therefore appears but that they have hitherto conſcienci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170477:40"/>and judiciouſly made uſe of His Majeſties Favour; and with great thankfulneſs have they expreſſed their ſence thereof, in their acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to God and men: His Royal and Paternal Charity is precious to them.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſe that ſome of this way were guilty of ſome provoking for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs, ſhould grave Patriots and wiſe Counſellors thereupon deſtroy the weak Part, or rather heal it? A prudent Father is not ſo provoked by the ſtubbornneſs of a Child as to caſt him out, and make him deſperate whileſt there is yet hope concerning him. It is meet indeed for Princes to expreſs their juſt indignation, when Subjects preſuming on their clemency do not contain themſelves within their duty; and the ſeaſonable expreſſion of ſuch diſdain, wiſely managed, is of great force in Government; never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs if it get the maſtery it is exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perillous. It was the Counſel of indignation that proceeded from <hi>Reho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boams</hi> young Counſellors.</p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:170477:41"/>
               <p>But there is yet a greater miſchief, when the cloud of this paſſion darkens the Underſtanding, that it cannot di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh between preſent diſ-ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and incurable pride and malice. When a peoples preſent diſ-ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on about remediable grievances, ſhall be deemed implacable enmity, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly pernicious counſels take place: Then it will be ſuggeſted to a Prince, that the Acts of Grace beſtowed upon ſuch a people make them but the more inſolent: For none may hope to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come pride by condeſcention, or inveterate malice by good turns; which is indeed a true ſaying, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted by miſ-application. In this caſe to judge rightly of things that differ, let a Prince conſider diligently whether the preſent averſneſs proceeds from rooted Principles, and a fixed Intereſt, inconſiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with the ſecurity of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate; or from the preſſures of the grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Party, in things which are not the neceſſary props of his Power, and without which his greatneſs may well
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170477:41"/>conſiſt; and let him never queſtion the gaining of ſuch a people whoſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and deſigns are not againſt the true and proper Intereſt of his Eſtate, whatſoever their preſent diſtempers be; for the grievances being redreſſed, time will wear out thoſe diſtempers: And in that caſe a people will not leſs value their Prince, becauſe he yieldeth to them with reſpect to his own concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; for they will not judge it a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced yielding, becauſe that proceeds from force which is yielded for preſent neceſſity, and againſt the main Intereſt; but they will cleave to him the more, by diſcerning that his and their good do agree in one; for it makes them hope that he will ſeek their good as his own. When Governours reſent the non-compliances of a party, their beſt remedy is to remove the occaſions, when it may be done without croſſing the Intereſts of State or maximes of Government; then will the honeſt-minded be mollified and moulded; and towards the reſidue of obſtinate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170477:42"/>if there be any ſuch, ſeverity will be uſed more ſuccesfully. It is the wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of rulers by all means to leſſen of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, and to contract the number of offenders: For where there are many ſufferers upon a Religious account, whether in truth or pretence, there will be a kind of glory in ſuffering, and ſooner or later it may turn to the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers detriment.</p>
               <p>Another great impediment of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick concord is an erroneous confidence in the more numerous Party, that they need not ſeek nor mind the way of peace; for they reckon themſelves ſure to carry it by the <hi>major</hi> Vote in all Councils and Conventions; they ſee wind and tide ſerving them: But they who conſider but few things, do make a ſudden judgment, which common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly falls ſhort. Great proſperity oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times blinds the wiſe as well as fools; and great advantages divert the mind from heeding many important circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of a buſineſs, that the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment made concerning it is moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect:
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170477:42"/>Wherefore in the preſent caſe it ſhould be minded, that the diſſenting party is not ſmall, that it is not made up of the rabble multitude, nor yet of Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natique ſpirits, but of honeſt and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber people, who act from principles of knowledge, and can render a reaſon of their practice, in things pertaining to conſcience, with as much diſcretion as any ſort of men in the Nation; that the inſtances which they make do not concern by matters and mutable occaſions, but matters of conſcience, that will never ceaſe nor vary; that they are not a Party far diſtant, but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry near; I mean not only in reſpect of place (for ſo the <hi>Papiſts</hi> that live a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us cannot be far from us) but of agreement in Principles of Religion, that they cannot be well ſevered nor kept in a divided State, nor yet be root<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out; but they will grow up under the influence of the Doctrine profeſſed in the Church of <hi>England;</hi> that in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny deliberations they may be able to put things to a ſtand, and in debates of
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170477:43"/>great conſequence to lead the indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ſort of men, and alſo many tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate ſpirits of the other perſwaſion, by the apparent equity of their propoſals.</p>
               <p>All theſe things and more of the like nature, do challenge a due regard from thoſe that would ſee through a buſineſs and make a perfect judgement. Beſides, the judicious ſhould conſider not onely the bulk and corps of a party, but what ſpirit doth quicken them, &amp; with what vivacity and conſtancy their motions do proceed, and their intereſt is pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu'd. It comes alſo within the compaſs of this inquiry to know the intrinſick ſtrength of the Hierarchy, and what they can do when they ſtand by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves alone, for their adventitious ſtrength may fail them. We need not tell them, that on their ſide at preſent the advantage is very great, yet haply it may appear in ſhew greater then it is indeed. Though the Engliſh Nation appear to affect a ſtated Order in the Church, nevertheleſs they may not ſerve the deſigns of the Hiearchy, nor
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170477:43"/>yet be conſcious thereof. Upon the late great revolution, the multitude do eaſily run from one extream to an other, thinking they can not run too far from thoſe troubles and diſcompoſures which laſt oppreſſed them. But as the prudent ponder their paths at preſent, ſo the paſſionate multitude may at length know where they are, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern alike the evil of both extreams. Many that are lifted up may give of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and fall under great diſpleaſure; they that are caſt down, may be better adviſed by their ſufferings, and remove the occaſions of ſtumbling, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, if not indeared, yet inoffenſive to the Nation. Such viciſſitudes of love and hatred do happen in every age, and there is no new thing under the Sun.</p>
               <p>An other Obſtacle in the way of this conjunction is an opinion of many, that the ſure and only means of preventing ſchiſm, and maintaining unity in the Church, is by multiplying Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial injunctions and Canons, by requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring full conformity to controverted
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170477:44"/>forms which might well be ſpared, by exacting not onely ſubmiſſion of pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, but aſſent of judgement declared by ſubſcription to all particulars of Doctrine, Worſhip and Diſcipline, in ever jot and tittle thereof. But in very deed this is the ſure way of endleſſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention among a people that are not bottomed on this principle of belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving as the Church believes. This kind of impoſing hath diſcompoſed all Chriſtendom, and rends the ſeverall Churches from each other, and makes the rent incurable. It is the way of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> upon this account is guilty of the fouleſt ſchiſm that was ever made in the Chriſtian world. It is a notable ſaying of <hi>Chillingworth—Not Proteſtants for rejecting, but the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>for impoſing on the faith of Chriſtians, Doctrines unwritten and unneceſſary, and for diſturbing the Churches peace, and dividing unity in ſuch matters, is in a high degree preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and ſchiſmatical</hi>—God is jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous for his worſhip, and conſciences
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170477:44"/>well informed and duly tender are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe jealous concerning it, leſt they ſhould provoke God to jealouſie. Minds truly religious doe ſet an high price on matters of conſcience, and will expoſe all to ſail rather then croſs their principles. Wherefore if in matters of perpetual controverſie between god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſe perſons, the Church ſhall make peremptory decrees and ſevere injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, it muſt needs diſſolve the band of unity. But the beſt and ſureſt means of preventing and ſuppreſſing Schiſms, is to prevent corrupt adminiſtrations, and real ſcandals in matters Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, and ſeaſonably to reform abuſes, and not to interpoſe in leſſer differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, a great prejudice is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up againſt Biſhops ruling in conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation with Presbyters, and againſt Claſsicall, or Presbyterian meetings as inclining to Faction, and likely to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce alterations, which evils are ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to follow the diſtributing of the power among many. Whereupon the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170477:45"/>Government of a ſingle Perſon, or a Biſhop having ſole juriſdiction, is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended to be the ſureſt means of keeping Church affairs in a fixed ſtate: This prejudice having a great ſhew of truth, we muſt ſtoop to pry into it more narrowly. And firſt we have this poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical maxime to direct us in this inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that the condition of the people to be governed is the beſt rule of diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the apteſt form of Government. And according to this principle we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve, that abſolute Prelacy is the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Government to hold a people, that content themſelves with a cuſtomary ſervice, and the Religion of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and of their fore-fathers, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be. All Diſcourſes, Debates, Diſputations, and all occaſions of aon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt touching Religion, and particularly that exe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ciſe which is called propheſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, muſt be avoided. But this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is not ſo agreeable to a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that are given to ſearch the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and try Doctrines. In <hi>England</hi> where the inferior Clergy or parochial
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170477:45"/>Miniſtery is not rude and ignorant, but in a great part learned &amp; conſcientious, where the common people in a great part try all things, that they may hold faſt that which is good, the Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call juriſdiction can not conveniently reſide in a Prelate alone governing by ſevere Canons, and denouncing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication againſt all thoſe that expreſs any diſſent from any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of the received Forms of Worſhip and Diſcipline. For among ſuch a people, this is a likelier way to beget ſome great diſtemper, then to keep all in quietneſs and deep ſilence. But a form of Government more free by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributing the power among many, and regular meetings for free debates with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in certain limits will be much more peaceable and ſuccesful. It is here ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged that in ſuch an order of things diſſentions may ariſe, and cauſe ſome interruptions. Nevertheleſs no great inconvenience, but ſometimes much advantage may follow. The ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of warm conteſts may be unadvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170477:46"/>condemned. For as Thunder purgeth the Air, ſo theſe ſtirrings may purge the Church from Corruptions ingendering in it. Let the frame and order of things be ſo eſtabliſhed, that both parties may be made hopeleſs concerning factious attempts of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting this or that extream, that the conteſts may not be on the one ſide for Dominion, nor on the other ſide for inordinate liberty, but on both ſides for Truths due freedom, and then they will end in peace. If great miſtakes ſhould ariſe in ſuch meetings, and ſeem for a while to paſs currently, there may be found ſome perſons of that wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, integrity and reputation, as to be able to ſhew the fallacy, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince thoſe of both ſides that intend uprightly. In which caſe, if they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive an evil ſpirit on work, and an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil deſign hatching among ſome, they will turn away with indignation from the contrivers of ſuch miſchief. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let the frame of Eccleſiaſtical po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity lean neither towards Tyranny nor
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170477:46"/>Anarchy, but be ſet upright for juſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty. Let good orders be kept, and priviledges not violated, and the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter number of thoſe who mean honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly will not be led into the ſnare of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. And ſelfiſh ambitious pragma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick ſpirits that trouble them will eaſily be detected and abandoned.</p>
               <p>Unto this reaſoning let the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of an eminent pacifick Biſhop be ſuperadded, concerning the way of order and ſtability in the conjunction of Epiſcopacy and Presbytery. Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi> in his Diſcourſe, Intituled, <hi>A mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt offer of ſome meet conſiderations to the Aſſembly of Divines at</hi> Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, commends the method of the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> for prevention of Error and Hereſie by a gradual pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from the parochial meering to the Presbytery, from thence to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial Synod, and from thence to the general Aſſembly for determining any controverſie, ſaying—<hi>This bears the face of a very fair and laudable courſe, and ſuch as deſerves the approbation of
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:170477:47"/>all the well-willers to that Diſcipline.</hi>—But let me add, That either we have or may have (in this very ſtate of things, with ſome ſmall variation) in effect the very ſame Government with us. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Presbyteries conſiſting of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Paſtors, we have our combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Miniſters in our ſeveral Dean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, over whom the rural Dean is cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen every year, by the Miniſters of that Diviſion, as their Moderator. This Deanry or Presbytery may be enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to meet every moneth, or oftner, in ſome City or Town next to them; and there they may have their exerciſe of Prophecying, as I have known it pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed in ſome parts of this Kingdom, as it is earneſtly wiſhed and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by that Excellently Learned Lord <hi>Verulam</hi> in his prudent Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations; where if any Queſtion fail of determination, it may be referred gradually from the leſſer to the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Aſſemblies, till it be brought to a National Synod. In the ſame diſcourſe the ſaid Biſhop commends one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170477:47"/>prudent, vigilant Overſeer, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peradded to a Grave, Judicious Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery, without concurrence of which Presbytery, the Biſhop or Overſeer ſhould not take upon him to inflict Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, or any other impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Cenſure,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Having diſcovered certain gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Impediments, I proceed to Argue upon the particular Concernments of the King, of the Nobility and Gentry, and of the Epiſcopal Clergy.</head>
               <p>His Majeſties Concernment in this grand Affair tranſcends the particular concernments of all others, whether Parties or Perſons, and that beyond all compariſon: Others may advance them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and Families by the preſent oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, and give over in time when they have builded their own houſes. Many, and perhaps the moſt, if chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges come, may retreat and ſerve the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170477:48"/>Times for their own ſecurity; but the King never deſcends from the Stage of publick Action, and can never ceaſe to be intereſſed in His people. Others having much to get and little to loſe, may make themſelves by preſent ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages; but the King hath little to get, but much to ſecure; and not the preſent occaſional and mutable advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, but perpetual ſtability is His In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt. His Majeſty hath worthily gained the Reputation of a Wiſe and Gracious Prince, of an excellent ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and temper for theſe times: And truly a Prince as wiſe as <hi>Solomon,</hi> hath no Wiſedom to ſpare from the weight of theſe buſineſſes. Let the God of the ſpirits of all fleſh, and the Father of Lights, continually give to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty a large heart, and comprehenſive Underſtanding, that may ſee far and near, and fetch within its compaſs all circumſtances, conſequents and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that are requiſite to the forming of a perfect judgment concerning theſe great Affairs.</p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:170477:48"/>
               <p>After ſo long a War between King and Parliament, and after all the chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in Government, the King being at length reſtored to His full Power and Greatneſs, and the people being ſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated with Civil Wars, tumults and changes; it may be concluded, that they will not eaſily run the hazard of abetting any Parties, in contradiction to Him: But this is happily or unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily ſuggeſted, as it is turned to a good or a bad uſe: Though evil Counſels may turn it to a bad uſe, yet it yields un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable advantage to the wholeſome Coueſels both of King and People, for the good of both. The people knowing that acquieſcence in preſent things is their beſt ſecurity, will not be given to change; and the King knowing the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples indiſpoſition to abet a change, will have little occaſion of jealouſie. And their mutuall confidence, which is the ſtrongeſt bond of peace, will lead them without rub or let into a ſetled mutuall happineſs. But it is not good advice to neglect a peoples intereſt, or to uſe
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170477:49"/>them with leſs regard, becauſe they are willing to hug their own peace in any tolerable condition. The Soveraigns greatneſſe, and the peoples freedome, are but one frabrick reſting upon the ſame fundamental conſtitution. If you ſhake the one, you ſhake the other alſo. I deteſt and abhorre the tumults and inſurrections of the people, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of the Soveraign power. Let wickedneſs proceed from the wicked. But let none that ſeek a righteous end tread in unrighteous wayes: let no wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded perſon be drawn into ſuch a ſnare of reproach and ruine. I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that the generality of the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian denomination would indure extremities, before they would revenge or defend themſelves by unlawfull means, as rebelling againſt their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Soveraign. As I finde my own heart, ſo do I judge of others. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs let a wiſe Prince conſider, that the divine providence can by ways without number change the face and ſtate of things, when a disſatisfied con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170477:49"/>party ſhall not ſtir one foot to indeavour a change. Wherefore let Counſels of ſafety and ſtability take place, that a Princes intereſt may ſtand firm againſt all aſſaults of unexpected accidents.</p>
               <p>It hath been judged a Maxime in Policy, that to head faction is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to one aſpiring to ſoveraignty, but not to one poſſeſſed of it. Alſo that to uphold diviſion is the way to ſubdue a people, but not to hold them in firm obedience, when ſubdu'd. <hi>Machiavel</hi> ſhews the inconvenience that ariſeth to a Prince by holding a people under his Government divided into factions, becauſe he will be inclined (as all by nature are) to take part in any thing that is divided, and to be pleaſed more with this then with that party, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the other is diſcontented. And he brings in a pertinent ſtory, That in the year 1501. a Gentleman ſent by the King of <hi>France</hi> into <hi>Italy,</hi> to cauſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of certain loſt Towns to the <hi>Florentines,</hi> finding in every one of
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:170477:50"/>thoſe Fortreſſes men, who, when they came to viſit him, ſaid, that they were of ſuch a faction, much blamed their diviſion, ſaying, that in <hi>France,</hi> if one of the Kings ſubjects ſhould ſay he were of the Kings party, he ſhould be puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, becauſe ſuch a ſpeech would ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie no leſs then that there were in the Country people enemies to the King; whereas the King willeth that all thoſe Towns be his friends, and united with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in themſelves. Let me rehearſe the Counſell of our late Soveraign to His Majeſty that now is—<hi>Take heed of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betting any Faction, or applying to any publick diſcriminations in matters of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, contrary to what is in your own judgment, and the Churches well ſettled. Your partial adhering as head to any one ſide, gains you not ſo great advantages in ſome mens hearts, who are prone to be of their Kings Religion, as it loſeth you in others, who think themſelves and their profeſsion firſt deſpiſed, then perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by you. Take ſuch a courſe as may either with calmneſſe and charity
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170477:50"/>quite remove the ſeeming differences and offences by impartiality; or ſo order affairs in point of power, that you need not to fear or flatter any Faction</hi>— Now if the caſe were ſuch, that one party were the Kings onely Confidents, and that the other cannot be faithful to him upon immutable grounds and reaſons, then policy would adviſe him ſo to order things in point of power, that he need not fear nor flatter the adverſe party. But it is evident that the Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans love the King, and Kingly Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and account themſelves happy in His Majeſties clemency, allowing them a juſt and inoffenſive liberty in certain matters of Conſcience. It is alſo evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to all impartial Judgements, that his Majeſties calmneſs and charity may remove the ſeeming differences, and offences on their part. They are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to comply with Epiſcopacy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulated, and Liturgy corrected; and they preferre union by accommodati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before Toleration with Diviſion.</p>
               <p>If it be objected, that the King by
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170477:51"/>carrying an even hand between both parties will inſure neither, for both will remain disſatisfied; I reply, this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were of force, if the differences muſt remain uncompounded, and the parties publickly divided into two op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite ſocieties; but we lay this for a ground-work, that theſe twain are to be made one as to publick communion in divine worſhip, and to an agreement in one common intereſt relating both to the Proteſtant Religion and to this Kingdom, which his Majeſties wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome may accompliſh by a prudent diſpoſing of thoſe things which indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently belong to both, and wherein they both agree; and in divers things that are peculiar to this or that ſide, he may gratifie the one and the other with moderation, as when the favours vouchſafed to the one are not injurious to the others peace. In which caſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, here may remain men of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent perſwaſions, but not of divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded parties and intereſts. Beſides if ſome on either hand ſhould become
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170477:51"/>turbulent, and cry we will have all or none, yet the greater number, yea the main body of either ſide may be found of calmer judgements and affections, who together with a multitude of wiſe and well minded perſons that are indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent between both perſwaſions, would cauſe the violent ones to keep within bounds. And as many of thoſe paſſionate men, as have any judgment, will diſcern, that they are without hope of prevailing, and diſadvantage themſelves by oppoſing the common intereſt and quiet of the Nation.</p>
               <p>His Majeſty is a great King, he is King indeed, and reigns in great power over a willing people. He hath in his hands the joynt ſtock or common in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the whole Nation. Neither of theſe grand parties can ſubſiſt without him; and this gives him aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, that they are and muſt be both his. It is manifeſt that his intereſt hath gotten the preheminence over all partial intereſts, as indeed it ought. For if the Prince be not in this regard tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170477:52"/>he is ready to be laid low. Wiſe men inform us, that a Prince by adhering to one Faction, may in time lift it up above his own Imperial inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, which will be forced to give way to it as the leſſer to the greater. And the prime leaders of the potent Faction will ſway more then the Prince himſelf. They will become arrogant, unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and boundleſs in their ambitious deſigns. It is obſerved by <hi>Henry</hi> the Third of <hi>France,</hi> that he would be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken into the League with the Princes of his own Kingdom to root out the proteſtants, and after awhile the ſame League was turned againſt him. A Prince may be ſo intangled, that he ſhall not know how to winde out of thoſe wayes wherein he hath ſo far in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged himſelf; neither ſhall he be able to turn himſelf to the neceſſity of his own affairs as new accidents ariſe. Then is a Prince truely potent when he hath all particular Factions lying at his feet, and can compell them to live in peace with one another. This is the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:170477:52"/>of our ſoveraign Lord this day. For he is alone, and there is none be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides him, on whom the Nation can have any ſtable dependence. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let His Majeſties high concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments be the <hi>primum mobile</hi> to carry about all the inferiour Orbs in our po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litical world.</p>
               <p>His Majeſty hath gained his peoples hearts, and is glorious in their eyes, and by his continued clemency he will not fail to hold them faſt to himſelf. He deſires to govern well, and they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be well governed, and ſeek no greater liberty. In ſome tender points of Conſcience they wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> upon his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence, and are willing to cloſe with uniformity, not in rigour, but in ſome convenient latitude and relaxation. There is an yeelding that is no way ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, but generous and advantageous, a princely condeſcention, whereby a King becomes more abſolute, and may have what he will from his loving ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. And they will no leſs fear him then love him, as knowing both his
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170477:53"/>goodneſs and his greatneſs. For he is great indeed to whom the hearts of three Nations are linked; and it is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally impoſſible that ſo vaſt a people ſhould at once be loſt to a King who continues to deſerve well of them, and to make them his favourites. And then what perſon or party ſhaldare to ſleight his Government, whoſe intereſt and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence is of ſo large extent?</p>
               <p>There is a ſaying, which by many hath been taken up for a proverb. <hi>No Biſhop, no King.</hi> I do not well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the riſe of this ſaying, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore dare not ſpeak in derogation of their judgements who were the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors it. But upon the matter it ſelf, I crave to make this modeſt Animadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. And firſt it is ſome degrading to the tranſcendent intereſt of Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to affix unto it a neceſſity of any one partial intereſt for its ſupport: for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependency and ſelf-ſubſiſtence, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out leaning upon any Party, is a Prince his ſtrength and glory. Alſo it makes that Party over confident, and its op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170477:53"/>too deſpondent: Such ſayings as import a Princes neceſſary depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence on any particular Party, may in the mouthes of ſubjects be too pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous, and in the mouth a Prince too unwary. But of this particular I dare not ſo ſpeak, in as much as I know not its riſe and reaſon. Onely this I humbly conceive, that the coalition of Epiſcopacy and Presbytery, ſets forth a Biſhop in conjunction with Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, of no leſs dependence on the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, and of more influence on the people, then a Biſhop having ſole ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction can have in the preſent age.</p>
               <p>As concerning the Nobility and Gentry of this Kingdom, who for the greater part are ſaid to favour Prelacy, They cannot in reaſon be offended at ſuch a regulated Epiſcopacy, when they ſhall behold its order and harmony, and tendency to ageneral peace. It ſeems agreeable to their Nobleneſs, to affect a comely and venerable Order in the Church for the honour of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:170477:54"/>And let them judge whether the Worſhip of God be more holy and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend for thoſe many Geſticulations and various poſtures enterchangeably uſed in parts of divine Service that are of the ſame kind, and require equall Reverence. Whether a grave habit of civil decency for a Miniſter, is leſs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent in ſacred Adminiſtrations then certain other Veſtments which ſome ſcruple, as conceiving that holineſs is placed in them? Whether a Church ſettled by limited Epiſcopacy, cannot attain to its due veneration without the Hierarchical dominion and ſplendor. The reduction of abſolute Prelacy to Epiſcopall preſidency here deſired, may concern the Nobility and Gentry as well as others. For as others may be oppreſſed, ſo theſe may be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>topped. Exceſſive power is common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exerciſed beyond their intentions, that are eager to ſet it up. And they that thought onely of cruſhing a party offenſive to them, may at length finde themſelves obnoxious, or at leaſt neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:170477:54"/>and undervalued. On the other ſide, they have little cauſe to fear that which is commonly ſo much dreaded, namely the exceſſive rigour of diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline from a preſident Biſhop, and grave Presbyters joyntly governing. For it is ſuppoſed that no act of Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline ſhall be exerciſed againſt or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Laws of the Land, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be made without conſent of the Nobles and Commons in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>Let the Epiſcopal Clergy admit an addreſs to themſelves touching their own concernments: Peradventure they either ſuſpect or diſdain the counſel of one that may ſeem an adverſary; but whatever they apprehend, it is the counſel of one who with his whole heart deſires that they may not miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, who accounts them too precious to beloſt to their brethren, if they will permit themſelves upon any reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble tearms to be gained; who would gladly walk with them by the ſame Rule in things received in common,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:170477:55"/>which are ſufficient for Chriſtian con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, and ſhould be ſo acknowledged by all that mind the things of Chriſt more then their own things. Were I a true hater of that Party, or a right Phanatick, I ſhould wiſh for their vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent irruption upon the Prebyterians, even as vehemently as now I purſue the deſign of peace; and I verily think my reaſoning, however it takes with them, will convince them of my good intention: If they decline moderate counſels, and reſolve to run high, they may attain to a lofty ſtanding; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit they will always ſtand on a pina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle: In a little time they have greatly inlarged their borders and lengthened their cords; it were good that now they ſhould ſtrengthen their ſtakes and make good their ground. By modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion only can they be eſtabliſhed. Some may ſay in their hearts, <hi>The bricks are fallen down, but we will build with hewen ſtones; the Syco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mores are cut down, but we will change them into Cedars.</hi> Indeed their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:170477:55"/>is well known; nevertheleſs let them conſider their conſtant ſtrength, and accordingly limit their hopes; for this is an high point of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Let them that have gotten a victory uſe it wiſely, and take care that they loſe it not in hope of a greater. The iſſue of things oft times have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved unfortunate to thoſe that have waxed inſolent and unreaſonable upon unexpected ſucceſſes. There is not a greater errour then to refuſe tearms of Agreement that are profered by a Party, which cannot be rooted out, but will be alwaies conſiderable either as friends or enemies, eſpecially when thoſe tearms do compriſe ſome part of their victory that ſhould accept them. Let the Epiſcopal Clergy obſerve the ſpirit of the Nation, and the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Times, that they may right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly comprehend the meaſure of their own hopes. The Engliſh are a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Nation, and as they delight in the Majeſty and Glory of their King, ſo alſo in the ſplendid condition of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:170477:56"/>Governours, that their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of living be in ſome ſort conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the dignity and opulency of the Nation: Accordingly they ſeem to take pleaſure that the Eccleſiaſtical State be upheld by a fair Revenue and competent Dignity, yet with modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: For if the Clergy do riſe to Princely or Lordly wealth and power, they may become the envy of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and Gentry: Let them remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, they ſtand by Grace, not by their own ſtrength, but by their Prince His Favour. The Nation in general may be taken with a grave and maſculine decency in all Sacred things ſutable to their ſpiritual Majeſty; but I make a Queſtion whether in this noon-tide of the Goſpel they will fall in love with exceſſive gaudineſs, pompous ſhews, and various affected geſtures in Sacred Adminiſtrations; and not rather eſteem them vanities too much detracting from the dignity and purity of Goſpel Worſhip. In this noon-tide of the Goſpel the Biſhops cannot magnifie
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:170477:56"/>their Office but by other courſes then what were taken in former and darker times. Meer formalities will no long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er dazle our eyes: We ſhall think they have work of an higher nature, then to look only to the obſervation of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Forms, and Rites, and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies: they muſt make a nearer approach to the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> practice in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Preaching of the Word, in the ſtrict obſervation of the Lords Day, in keeping a true watch over the Flock, and in correcting the real ſcandals that break forth in mens converſations: And if they walk in theſe paths, the <hi>Prelatiſts</hi> and <hi>Presbyterians</hi> will not be far aſunder. Perhaps the friends of <hi>Prelacy</hi> may imagine, that in this coa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lition <hi>Presbytery</hi> may at length under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine <hi>Epiſcopacy;</hi> but reaſon ſhews, that <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> will ſtand more firm in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with <hi>Presbytery,</hi> then by it ſelf alone.</p>
               <p>In the body natural there is ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant humour, as <hi>ſanguine, chole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick, melancholy,</hi> or <hi>phlegmatick;</hi> yet
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170477:57"/>none of theſe do ſubſiſt alone, without the mixture of the reſt in a due tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rament. In like manner the Body Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical may be of ſeveral complex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions or conſtitutions, as <hi>Epiſcopal,</hi> or <hi>Presbyterial,</hi> according to the predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant quality. Now if the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Churches would become more firm and ſtable by the ſuperintendency of one grave Preſident, (and the truth is in all <hi>Presbyteries</hi> there appeareth ſome <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> either formal or vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al) ſo an <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> Church may be judged more firm and ſtable by a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops ſuperintendency in conſociation with aſſiſtant <hi>Presbyters.</hi> And to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the fear of the incroachments of <hi>Presbytery,</hi> it is eaſie to diſcern, that <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> if it contains its ſelf within moderate bounds, will be always in this National Church the predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant quality.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:170477:57"/>
               <head>In the Concluſion of this Diſcourſe, let me offer theſe few Eſſayes concerning the pathes of peace.</head>
               <p>The glorifying and pleaſing of the higheſt Potentate and univerſall Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, and the eternall happineſs of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal precious ſouls, are the moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and bleſſed ends of Government. Let his Majeſties Raign be happy and glorious in attaining theſe ends. A Chriſtian King eſteems it the excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of his regal Power to hold and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage it as the ſervant of Jeſus Chriſt, to be a Protector of the true Church, the Body of Chriſt the Lambs wife, for whoſe redemption Chriſt dyed, and for whoſe gathering and perfecting, the world is continued. It is the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of this true Church, to make the holy Scriptures the perfect rule of their faith and life, to worſhip God in ſpirit and in truth, according to the power and ſpiritual worſhip of the Goſpel, to
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:170477:58"/>walk by the rule of the new Creature in ſpiritual mortification and crucifixi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the world, to ſtudy holineſſe in ſincerity, to ſtrive to advance it in themſelves and others, and to have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon others unto ſound knowledge, faith, humility, godlineſſe, juſtice, temperance, charity. The true Church lies in the middle between two extreams, Formaliſts and Fanaticks. They are of circumſpect and regular walking, no way forward in attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or deſiring alterations in a civill State. A Prince doth hold them in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience under a double bond. For they know they muſt needs be ſubject not onely for wrath, but for conſcience ſake. Indeed we will not conceal, that in lawful wayes they aſſert that liberty which is ſetled by the known Lawes and fundamentall Conſtitutions, the maintaining whereof is the Prince's as much as the Peoples ſafety.</p>
               <p>That being the happieſt Politie that is founded in true Religion, and moſt fully ſuited to mens everlaſting con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:170477:58"/>it greatly behoveth Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors to mark and avoid thoſe things, which bring Religion into contempt, and tend to the increaſe of Atheiſm and infidelity. The many various Sects and abſurd opinions and fancies, and pretended Revelations of theſe latter times, have much leſſened the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of Religion in <hi>England.</hi> This is a great evill, and much obſerved and decryed by the preſent times. There is an other evill no leſs injurious to the honour and eſtimation of Chriſtian piety, to wit, Ceremonial ſtrictneſſe with real prophaneſs, or at the moſt but lukewarmneſs in the real part of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. And this is the true ſtate of the Papacy, by occaſion whereof Atheiſts have ſo abounded in <hi>Italy. Machiavel</hi> obſerves in his time, that Chriſtianity was no where leſs honoured then in <hi>Rome,</hi> which is the pretended Head thereof. Let this evil be ſeen, prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and remedied, that the ſacred name of the Church be given to a ſociety not carnal, but truly ſpirituall, according
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:170477:59"/>to that of the Apoſtle, <hi>We are the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion which worſhip God in the ſpirit, and rejoyce in Chriſt Jeſus, and have no confidence in the fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is the preheminence of His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, as General Biſhop of the Land, (for ſo He is in a political ſence) to viſit His people of all ranks by His prudent inſpection: And it is worthy of His chiefeſt care and ſearch, to know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther every Paſtor be reſident with his own Flock, and doth conſtantly on e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Sabbath teach them the good Knowledge of God; what Pluraliſts do ſeize upon ſeveral Congregations, thruſting or barring out laborious Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d leaving the ſheep in the hands of one who is a meer mercinary, and careth not for them; whether Preaching in Cathedral Churches be more frequent ſince the reviving of Deans and Chapters then before, when thoſe places were ſupplied by one or two ſtipendiary Miniſters; whether the Precincts of Cathedrals be the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt parts of the Land, and the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:170477:59"/>thereof the pureſt parts of the Clergy, as in reaſon they ought to be, In all His Majeſties ſuperintendency there is nothing of greater moment, then to provide that the Order and Frame of Eccleſiaſticks have not a tendency to make the ſuperior Party proud and covetous, and the inferior poor and vicious.</p>
               <p>A good Conſtitution or Frame of Eccleſiaſtical Politie is incomparably more available to produce good ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, then good Canons or good Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours can be where the Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is naught: For in ſuch a ſtate good Canons and good Governours will not be able to reform abuſes and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect ſcandals, and promote the true end of Church Diſcipline.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>Trent</hi>-Council the Papalins or the Popes Creatures held this for a maxime, <hi>That the Decrees of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion could not diminiſh the profits of the Court of</hi> Rome, <hi>as long as the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Apoſtolique See was not impair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> The Council being ended, and the
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:170477:60"/>Decrees coming to be ratified by the Pope, and the Officers of the Court repreſenting their loſſes and prejudices by the Ratification, and the Pope there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by perplexed, and the Cardinals divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in their Opinions, one <hi>Biſhop,</hi> a man well converſant in Court Affairs, ſaid, <hi>That he could not chuſe but wonder at this great fear, concerning the confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Decrees, which he ſaw did ariſe without reaſon; for that Laws have no power but what is given them by him that Governeth; That the Pope by his Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition might give them a larger or a ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſence; yea, and contrary to that which the words do import, That he might or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain a particular Congregation for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding the Council, and effectually pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide that none ſhould be able to alleadge the Decrees in prejudice of the Court.</hi> The Pope was ſatisfied with theſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, being perſwaded that it would fall out as the Biſhop had ſaid: And ſo the Decrees of Reformation proved of no effect to reform the enormities of the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi> By this it appears,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:170477:60"/>that new Laws and Decrees work little where a corrupt Frame remaineth ſtill in force. If in ſuch a ſtate of things good men promoted to Government ſhould do their utmoſt to rule well, they are no more able to reform the Churches committed to them, then the two <hi>Cato's</hi> to reform the Roman Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, when it was wholly cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted and out of frame. Beſides, in a corrupt frame of Politie there are theſe two great evils, the one, that good men will ſoon degenerate; the other, that bad men led by ambition and avarice, will by Arts proper to the times more eaſily get promotions: and a good Prince ſhall ſee it and not know how to help it. That Politie, whether Civil or Eccleſiaſtical, is well conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted, that in its frame is apt to bridle humane deſires; but that is ill conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted which lets looſe the reins to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite. No function or calling is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from the corruption that is in the world through luſt. And the gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur of this world is not more peril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:170477:61"/>to any then to Eccleſiaſtical per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
               <p>It is a ſingular excellency in any frame of Politie, that the power of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good be very ample, and that a power to hurt be as much contracted and reſtrained as the ends of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will permit: And verily no wiſe and gracious perſons would willingly be tempted with a power to hurt, if they be ſufficiently impowered to do good without it: Beſides, it is an odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous power, and makes the Office hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. Now the way to this happy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of things is obvious. Let not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere Laws and Canons, concerning things diſputable and unneceſſary, which may inſnare the conſciences of godly, orthodox and peaceable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, remain in force. The moſt zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous aſſertors and rigid impoſers of Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies acknowledge, that they are not neceſſary parts of Worſhip: the declaring, That holineſs is not to be placed in them, is their beſt defence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the charge of wil-worſhip. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:170477:61"/>to ſuſpend and ſilence able and painful Miniſters, to vex and puniſh o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther godly Chriſtians that cannot ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to thoſe Ceremonies, is to procure much evil without a benefit to counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail it. A power of doing much harm and little good, is unhappily placed in any ſort of men, but eſpecially in Chriſts ſpiritual officers, who accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Apoſtles words, have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved authority from the Lord, for edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and not for deſtruction.</p>
               <p>The moſt renowned Polititian ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, that thoſe Kingdoms, Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, and ſects of Religions ſubſiſt longeſt, that are often renewed or brought back to their firſt beginnings. For the beginnings of all theſe muſt needs contain ſome goodneſs in them, by means whereof they riſe to their firſt reputation and increaſe. Now in proceſs of time that goodneſs will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e overgrown by corruption; and unleſſe ſomething happen to reduce it to the juſt mark, thoſe Societies muſt needs be deſtroyed. And touching Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:170477:62"/>he proves theſe Reformations ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary by the example of the Roman Religion, ſaying, — <hi>If it had not been reduced again to its principles by St.</hi> Francis, <hi>and St.</hi> Dominick, <hi>it would have been quite defaced. For theſe by their poverty and imitation of Chriſts life, made a new impreſsion thereof in mens minds, which was quite blotted out thence, and their new rules were ſo powerful, and are now the cauſe that the diſhoneſty of the Prelates and Heads of Religion do not ruine it, partly by their living in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, and partly by the credit they have in confeſsing the people and preaching to them.</hi>— Indeed this Author doth not hit the mark, (and no marvel) touching the true principles of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, and right imitation of Chriſt, the reviving whereof he aſcribes to thoſe two popiſh Saints; but his reaſon of Religion in general is ſolid and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and his inſtances in particular are right and ſound, being applyed (as they are) to the upholding of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Religion. As for Religion truly
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:170477:62"/>Chriſtian, the way to preſerve it in its power and glory, is frequently to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce it to its firſt beginnings; for then was its goodneſs moſt eminent. The primitive ſpirit of the Chriſtian Church was a ſpirit of power and glory, and the primitive order was moſt ſpiritual and powerful. Let Chriſts holy Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, let Apoſtolicall precept and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice be the pattern of our Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. What ſound Proteſtant will deny the holy Scriptures to be a perfect rule of all divine Inſtitutions? To them we appeal, by them would we ſtand or fall; and they mention no Miniſters of the Goſpel, that were not Biſhops ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the flock. But in purſuance of peace, touching the matter of Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy, the moderate Presbyterians are willing to deſcend to the times lower by one degree, and to come to the Ages next following the Scripture-times, and to accept what they do preſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, to wit, a Preſident-Biſhop ruling in conſort with Presbyters, and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer not of an other Order then Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:170477:63"/>but of an higher degree in the ſame Order. We appeal to thoſe times concerning this matter. And they that admire and almoſt adore antiquity, ſhould not deny our juſt appeal.</p>
               <p>And wherein ſtands the power and glory of the Church militant? Doth it ſtand in the pompous ſhews of Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious worſhip, with the gliſtering furniture thereof, in the ſecular digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and jurisdictions of the higher rank of Eccleſiaſticks, in the implicite faith of the Laiks, and in a formal unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity in the outſide of Religion? Or in the powerful preaching of the Goſpel by able Miniſters of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in the lively and ſpiritual manner of prayer, in the diſpenſation of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments after a manner moſt effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al to the increaſe of knowledge, ſaith, and virtue, in the exerciſe of diſcipline to correct all contumacious diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence againſt the known laws of Chriſt our King and Law-giver, and all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in a comly order with a grave and ſober decency? Let all unprejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:170477:63"/>minds give judgment, which of theſe two different ſtares of Religion doth moſt expreſs the Goſpel-mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, which is called the miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Spirit, and is incomparably more glorious and powerful, then the Moſaical diſpenſation with all its out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and viſible ſplendor. Let them alſo judge which of theſe two is moſt conformable to the ſtate of the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive times, wherein the Chriſtian Church, not by an arm of fleſh and the wiſdom of this world, but by weapons mighty through God, as the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical doctrine and diſcipline, the holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of believers, the conſtancy of Martyrs, overturned the Kingdom of Satan, and advanced the Kingdom of Chriſt, where Satans throne was, in oppoſition to the power of the Roman Empire, the wiſdom of the learned Heathens, the counſels of Polititians, the potency of ancient Cuſtoms, the inveterate prejudice of all ſorts of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and laſtly, in oppoſition to the Devil raigning and raging in them all.
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:170477:64"/>Wherefore let us minde the true way of reſtoring the Chriſtian Religion to its primitive power and glory.</p>
               <p>It is a happy frame and order, when things are ſetled for general ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that none or very few of the ſerious people deſire an alteration, but all, or moſt of them dread it; as alſo when things are ſetled for ſtability, that none, who have a will to it, can encompaſs an alteration. It is a happy thing to light upon the way that leads to this ſatisfaction, and to this ſtability. In religion the general way of ſatisfaction is not to gratifie the humour and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite of one or more parties, but to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the conſciences of the judicious and ſober-minded in general. For ſuch on all ſides will ſway moſt for conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance, and if they be ſatisfied, intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate and unquiet ſpiri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s would quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be out of breath in their raſh at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts. Likewiſe the way of ſtability, that none may ſucceſsfully project a change, is to prevent mens running in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to extreams on either hand. For when
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:170477:64"/>one extream prevaileth, a change eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly followeth. In this caſe it fares with the Church as with civil States. A principality heightned into Tyranny, tumbles down into Anarchy, and a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick too much cheriſhing popular extravagancies lifts up a tyranny. Now the way to prevent extreams, is either to chuſe moderate ſpirits, or elſe a bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancing number of the oppoſite parties to the managing of publick affairs. In which election a Prince doth not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear as a Neuter, but as a moderator and true Governour, that hath the command of all intereſts.</p>
               <p>And now having purſued Peace to the utmoſt of my ſmall ability in theſe pacifick Diſcourſes, I hope this dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent ſearch after the knowledg of good and evil in this kind will not be judged an eating of the forbidden fruit, an am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious and bold inquiry into things not to be made known. For it is not a curious or preſumptuous intruding in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Counſels of Princes, and ſecrets
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:170477:65"/>of Government; but a modeſt and ſober deliberation upon things open and manifeſt, &amp; of publick inquiſition and diſcourſe. Beſides, it is an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary time, wherein there are great thoughts, yea great ſearchings of heart in men of all degrees and all perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. It is true, that this Nation is not erecting a new Kingdom, nor laying new foundations of Government; yet it is no leſs true, that this reſtauration is as it were life from the dead, and we are in ſome ſort beginning the world a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new. It is a notable <hi>Epocha,</hi> or pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod of time, giving opportunity to cut off exceſſes, to make up defects, and to make crooked things ſtraight, before we be fixed and ingaged in particular wayes, from which though never ſo inconvenient, we may not be able to draw back or turn aſide. It is affirmed by one of piercing knowledge in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of this nature, that it is a profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble order in a Commonwealth, for any one to propoſe what is for the publick
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:170477:65"/>good. Surely the Kingdom cannot ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer by the propoſals of the meaneſt perſons, when they touch not upon the fundamental Conſtitution, nor diſturb publick peace and order. This Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe offers no diſturbance to ſuch Forms and Orders as have attained a quiet ſtated poſture in theſe times. The Laws have made ſome alteration in things of former uſe and practice, as the Act for aboliſhing the High Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. The times have made more alterations in mens minds and wayes; and his Majeſty hath obſerved a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, or at leaſt expediency of ſome alterations, whereby the minds of men may be compoſed, and the peace of the Church eſtabliſhed, declaring—<hi>That he hath not the leaſt doubt but the preſent Biſhops will think, that the Conceſsions made by him to allay the preſent Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, are very juſt and reaſonable.</hi>—</p>
               <p>Laſtly, The ſcope of this Treatiſe doth juſtifie and defend it ſelf, whereof the bare narration is a full Vindicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:170477:66"/>For the ſum of the whole matter is to perſwade a turning from the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of a partial Intereſt, and a turning to the obvious and eaſie way of giving generall ſatisfaction to all thoſe that acknowledge the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to be a true Church, and are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to abide in her Communion.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:170477:66"/>
            <head>An Advertiſment to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THere are lately Printed twenty two Sermons Preached upon ſeverall occaſions; By</hi> Edward Reynolds, <hi>D. in Divinity, and Biſhop of</hi> Norwich, <hi>in quarto; None of which are contained in his large Volume: And are to be ſold at the</hi> Roſe and Crown <hi>in St.</hi> Pauls Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:170477:67"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 78. line 5. read <hi>frowardneſs.</hi> p. 80. l. 5. r. <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicious.</hi> p. 18. l. 8. r. <hi>frowardneſs.</hi> p. 89. l. 6. r. <hi>ſale.</hi> p. 90. l. 19. r. <hi>conteſt.</hi> p. 119. l. 7. r. <hi>Clergy.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
